<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tragi-comoedia being a brief relation of the strange, and wonderfull hand of God discovered at Witny, in the comedy acted there February the third, where there were some slaine, many hurt, and several other remarkable passages : together with what was preached in three sermons on that occasion from Rom. 1, 18 : both which may serve as some check to the growing atheisme of the present age / by John Rowe ...</title>
            <author>Rowe, John, 1626-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6082</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11893675</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11893675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 509:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tragi-comoedia being a brief relation of the strange, and wonderfull hand of God discovered at Witny, in the comedy acted there February the third, where there were some slaine, many hurt, and several other remarkable passages : together with what was preached in three sermons on that occasion from Rom. 1, 18 : both which may serve as some check to the growing atheisme of the present age / by John Rowe ...</title>
                  <author>Rowe, John, 1626-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 81 [i.e. 79] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield, for Henry Cripps,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [Oxfordshire] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans I, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tragi-Comaedia.</hi> BEING A BRIEF RELATION OF THE STRANGE, AND Wonderfull hand of God diſcovered at WITNY, in the <hi>Comedy</hi> Acted there <hi>February</hi> the third, where there were ſome <hi>Slaine,</hi> many <hi>Hurt,</hi> with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall other <hi>Remarkable</hi> PASSAGES. Together with what was Preached in three Sermons on that occaſion from <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. Both which May ſerve as ſome Check to the Growing <hi>Atheiſme</hi> of the Preſent Age. By JOHN ROWE of G. C. C. in <hi>Oxford,</hi> Lecturer in the Towne of WITNY.</p>
            <q>
               <p>It is time for thee, Lord to work, for they have made voyd thy Law.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 119.126.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Verily he is a God that judgeth in the Earth.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 58.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Onatus apud Stobaeum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by L. LICEFIELD, For HENRY CRIPPS. Anno Dom. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epistle">
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:2"/>
            <head>TO MY HONOVRED and much beloved Friends, the Inhabitants of the Towne, &amp; Pariſh of WITNY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearely beloved in the LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE publiſhing of theſe few Papers, both the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent <hi>Narrative,</hi> and the enſuing <hi>Sermons</hi> of right belong to You, and you may challenge them as your owne. Among you it was that theſe wonders of the Lord were ſeen, and upon you it was that the Lord hath ſhewen himſelfe marvelous. Doe not quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the Almighty for ſetting you up as the publik Theatre whereon he would manifeſt his holyneſſe, juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, &amp; other Attributes to the world. We are his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and it were enough if we could ſay no more, but <hi>It is his pleaſure to have it ſo.</hi> Yet there is other reaſon why we ſhould quiet, and compoſe our ſelves,
<pb facs="tcp:50496:3"/>and ſhake off all thoughts, and reaſonings that are apt to ariſe, ſaying as the Church doth. <hi>We will beare the indignation of the Lord, becauſe we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt him.</hi> Though you are the people that doe only ſuffer, yet you are not they that are only aymed at. The Lord hath ſpoken from heaven to the whole Nation, by what he hath done amongſt you, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by a clear and eminent ſtroake againſt the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous unparraleld Atheiſme, irreligion, profaneſſe, which is walking up and downe in all places.</p>
            <p>Though the Lord hath began with you, yet he may not end with you. If his dealing with you make not others wiſe, their plagues may be farre greater then yours have been; and if ſo, it will be a mercy that you were corrected ſo ſoone, and not ſuffered to goe on in your ſinnes; which would have brought heavier ſorrowes in the end. Amongst you it was that theſe meane Sermons had their riſe, which were not in the leaſt intended for the Preſſe, when first they were Preached. But the deſires of ſome amongſt you to have written Coppies of them, the longings and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of others to have them publiſhed, the good of the Towne in generall (which might ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; laſting reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of theſe things) ſeemed to be ſome call to me for the publiſhing of them. To which I may adde the conſideration of ſome little good the Lord I hope was pleaſed to doe by theſe plain and meane Sermons: the hearts of ſome being a little awakened, and the affection of others ſtirred, and raiſed, and ſome provoked to attend on the word thereby. Which ſparks being of the Lords owne kindling, I thought it my duty to keep them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live as much as lay in me. I hope you will beare with
<pb facs="tcp:50496:3"/>my rudeneſſe of ſpeech, and plain ſpeaking: the Lord being my witneſſe, that it is not a pleaſure to me, to make bare your nakedneſſe, or diſcover your ſhame, my ayme only being, that you may lay to heart your ſinnes, ſeek pardon for them, and reformation of them. My care hath been as much as may be, to abſtain from all perſonall reflections, and not to make uſe of any ones Name, that I might not grieve the ſpirits of any by making them publike to the world, although if I had inſiſted on ſome particulars, the ſtory might have been ſet forth with more adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage in the eyes of ſome. Some enlargments there have been in the Sermons, &amp; ſome larger explications of a few Scriptures, it being not poſſible within ſuch a ſcantling of time, as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted, to ſpeake fully to all things. Yet this you will find, you have ſcarce any materiall paſſage omitted of what was Preached, and the Additions which are (I hope) not altogether unprofitable or unneceſſary. Some Notes are put into the Margin, which need not trouble the leſſe skilfull Reader, all obſcurity being avoyded in the body of the Sermons themſelves. My humble deſire, and requeſt to you is, that you will not lay aſide this little Book as ſoon as it comes into your hands, though the things are mean and contemptible, if you conſider the perſon, parts, and years of him that brings them unto you, and the manner of his delivering them; yet are they great, and of moment, if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him that ſends them to you, ſo farre forth as the mind of God is revealed in them, and his particular will made known concerning you. Some few houres will ſerve to Reade over the whole Book, and if at leaſure times, you put your Children or Servants to reade but a little, it may be better then to let it lye
<pb facs="tcp:50496:4"/>moulding in your Windows. Poſſibly you may meet with ſuch a remembrace, if the Lord work with it by his Spirit, as you may bleſſe him for all your dayes. I can only ſay as the Apoſtle doth with a little change. <hi>Brethren my hearts deſire, and prayer to God for the people of</hi> Witny <hi>is, that they may be ſaved.</hi> I trust the Lord hath ſome of his election yet ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongst you, ſure I am there are ſome of his called, and faithfull ones already to be found in the middeſt of you. How long I may be left to ſpeak to you, I know not. This I can aſure you, I pray, and ſigh at the throne of Grace for you, as well as I can. And I could wiſh I had better prayers, and more ſighs and groanes, then my poore barren heart can afford. There could not be a greater joy to me, then to ſee the Kingdome of our Lord Jeſus taking place in greaer power in your ſoules: to ſee that high valuation, and eager thirſts in the hearts of many of you after a poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, neglected, forſaken Christ, whom the world (but it may break our hearts to ſpeak it) begins to grow weary of, though the world be not worthy of ſuch a one.</p>
            <p>Now the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus bleſſe you with the knowledge of himſelfe, and this his deare Sonne, and grant that the ſavour of his knowledge may be ſpread amongſt you more abundantly. Theſe are the conſtant prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your unworthy Friend, and Servant, in the Goſpell</hi> John Rowe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:4"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE NARRATIVE OF The Play Acted at <hi>Witny</hi> the third of <hi>February</hi> 1652. Together <hi>with its ſad and Tragicall End.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT may not ſeem ſo proper, nor be ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to every Reader, to ſet down all the Circumſtances about this <hi>Play,</hi> foraſmuch that ſomewhat might be ſaid touching the riſe and originall of it, the nature of the <hi>Play</hi> it ſelf, and the book from whence it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the motives, grounds, and ends of the Actors, concerning all which I might ſpeak more then here ſhall be inſerted, having taken ſome paines to ſatisfie my ſelfe in thoſe particulars. But I thought it meet to inſiſt on thoſe things, which did moſt diſcover the hand of God in ſo eminent and remarkable a Providence, and lightly touch on other things, ſo far as they may give light to
<pb facs="tcp:50496:5"/>that which is the name. This <hi>Play</hi> was and old <hi>Play,</hi> and had been Acted by ſome of <hi>Santon-Har-court</hi> men many years ſince. The Title of it is, <hi>A most pleaſant Comedy of</hi> Mucedorus <hi>the Kings Sonne of Valentia, and</hi> Amadine <hi>the Kings Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Aragon: with the merry conceits of</hi> Mouſe, &amp;c. The Actors of the <hi>Play</hi> were Countreymen; moſt of them, and for any thing I can heare, all of <hi>Stanton-Harcourt</hi> Pariſh. The punctuall time of their firſt Learning the <hi>Play,</hi> cannot be certainly ſet downe: but this we have been told, they had been learning it ever ſince <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> and had been Acting privatly every week. This we are informed upon more certain grounds, that they began to Act it in a more publike manner about <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and Acted it three or foure times in their own Pariſh, they Acted it likewiſe in ſeverall neighbowring Pariſhes, as <hi>Moore, Stanlake, South-Leigh, Cumner.</hi> The laſt place that they came at was <hi>Witny,</hi> where it pleaſed the Lord to diſcover his diſpleaſure, againſt ſuch wicked and ungodly <hi>Playes</hi> by an eminent hand. Some few dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Play</hi> was to be Acted, one of <hi>Stanton</hi> came to the <hi>Baylife</hi> of <hi>Witny</hi> telling him <hi>that there were ſome Countrey men that had learn'd to make a Play, and deſired his Leave to ſhew it,</hi> his aime being (as the <hi>Baylife</hi> conceiv'd) that they might have the Liberty of the <hi>Towne-Hall.</hi> Leave alſo was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the other <hi>Baylife,</hi> but they being denied by both the <hi>Baylifs,</hi> they pitched on the <hi>White Hart,</hi> a chiefe Inne of the Towne to Act their <hi>Play</hi> there. The day when it was Acted, was the third of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:50496:5"/>the ſame day when many Godly People, Towneſmen and Schollars of <hi>Oxford,</hi> kept a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Day of <hi>Fast</hi> at <hi>Carfax.</hi> About ſeaven a Clock at Night they cauſed a Drum to beat, and a Trumpet to be ſounded to gather the People together. The people flocked in great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Men, Women, and Children, to the number (as is gueſs'd) of three Hundred, ſome ſay foure hundred, and the Chamber where the <hi>Play</hi> was Acted being full, others in the Yard preſſed ſorely to get in. The people which were in the Roome were exceeding Joviall, and merry before the <hi>Play</hi> began, Young men and Maides dancing together, and ſo merry and frolick were many of the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, that the Players could hardly get Liberty that they themſelves might Act, but at laſt a little Liberty being obtained, the <hi>Play</hi> it ſelf began. In the beginning of it Enters a Perſon that took the name of Comedie, and ſpeaks as follows.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Why ſo thus doe I hope to pleaſe;</l>
               <l>Muſick revives, and Mirth is tolerable,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comedie</hi> play thy part, and pleaſe:</l>
               <l>Make merry them that come to joy with thee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>With two or three verſes more.</p>
            <p>Vpon this enters <hi>Envy,</hi> another perſon, &amp; ſpeaks as followes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nay ſtay Minion ſtay there lyes a block;</l>
               <l>What all on mirth? I'le interrupt your tale,</l>
               <l>And mix your Muſick with a Tragickend.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Vpon which <hi>Comedie</hi> replyes. <hi>Envy</hi> makesan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer againe in ſeverall verſes, and among the reſt theſe:
<pb facs="tcp:50496:6"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Harken thou ſhalt heare noyſe</l>
                  <l>Shall fill the ayre with ſhrilling ſound,</l>
                  <l>And thunder Muſick to the Gods above.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Three verſes after it followes,
<q>
                  <l>In this brave Muſick <hi>Envy</hi> takes delight</l>
                  <l>Where I may ſee them wallow in their bloud,</l>
                  <l>To ſpurne at Armes &amp; Leggs quite ſhivered off,</l>
                  <l>And heare the cryes of many thouſand ſlaine.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After this <hi>Comedie</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Envy</hi> replies
<q>
                  <l>Trebble death ſhall croſſe thee with diſpight,</l>
                  <l>And make thee mourn where moſt thou joyeſt,</l>
                  <l>Turning thy mirth into a deadly dole,</l>
                  <l>Whirling thy pleaſurs with a peale of death,</l>
                  <l>And drench thy methods in a Sea of bloud.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which paſſages if the Reader carry along with him, he will ſee how farre they were made good by the Divine hand, both on the Actors and Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators. The matter of the <hi>Play</hi> is ſcurrilous, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, blaſphemous in ſeverall paſſages. One paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of it hath ſuch a bitter Taunt againſt all <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons</hi> under the name of <hi>Puritans,</hi> and at <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> it ſelfe, under the phraſe <hi>of obſerving Faſting days,</hi> that it may not be omitted, it was almoſt in the beginning of the <hi>Play,</hi> and they were ſome of the Clownes words when he firſt began to Act, <hi>Well Ile ſee my Father hang'd before Ile ſerve his Horſe any more, well Ile carry home my bottle of Hay and for once make my Fathers Horſe turne Puritan, and obſerve Faſting dayes, for he gets not a bitt.</hi> How remarkable was this that ſome of them that were called <hi>Puritans</hi> in the dayes of old, had ſpent that
<pb facs="tcp:50496:6"/>very day in <hi>Oxford</hi> in Faſting, and Prayer; and that the Lord by ſo eminent an hand ſhould teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie againſt ſuch, who were not only ſcoffers at <hi>Godly perſons,</hi> but at <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelfe. Another paſſage was of ſo horrid an aſpect, as that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor who was to ſpeak it durſt not vent it without a change. The verſes as they are Printed are theſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ah <hi>Bremo, Bremo,</hi> what a foyle hadſt thou, that yet at no time was afraid</l>
               <l>To dare the greatest Gods to fight with thee</l>
            </q>
            <p>At the end of which verſes it followeth, <hi>He ſtrikes:</hi> and probable enough it is, that he uſed ſome action at that time; but the words were ſo gaſtly, and had ſuch a face of impiety in them, that he durſt not ſay <hi>Gods,</hi> but (as one that excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him would have us believe) he ſai'd <hi>Gobs.</hi> And indeed ſo inſolent were theſe, and other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Play, that ſome of the Spectators thought they were not fit to be uſed, and when they heard them, wiſhed themſelves out of the roome. We might inſtance in ſome other paſſages, but there hath been enough already. The modeſt, and ingenuous reader would bluſh to read ſome paſſages. Thus had they continued their ſport for an hour, and halfe, as ſome of the Spectators ſay, but as is more probable, about two houres, for they were ordinarily three houres in acting it (as the Players ſay) and there were aboue two parts in three of the play that were paſſed over in this Action. At which time it pleaſed God to put a ſtop to their mirth, and by an immediate hand of his owne, in cauſing the chamber to ſink, and fall
<pb facs="tcp:50496:7"/>under them, to put an end to this ungodly Play before it was thought, or intended by them.</p>
            <p>The Actors who were now in action were <hi>Bremo a wild man,</hi> (courting, and ſolliciting his Lady, and among other things, begging a <hi>Kiſſe</hi> in this verſe.</p>
            <q>Come kiſſe me (Sweet) for all my favours past)</q>
            <p>And <hi>Amadine</hi> the Kings daughter (as named in the Play) but in truth a young man attired in a womans Habit. The words which were then ſpeaking, were theſe, the words of <hi>Bremo</hi> to his Lady
<q>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be fed with Quailes, and Partridges,</l>
                  <l>With Black-birds, Larkes, Thruſhes, and Nightingales.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Various reports there have been concerning the words ſpoken at that time, as that it ſhould be ſayed, <hi>the Devill was now come to act his part:</hi> ſome of the People might ſay ſo, obſerving the <hi>wild mans</hi> carriage, and ſome other paſſages that went before, where there was mention made of the Divell in a Bares dublet, the <hi>wild man</hi> then acting the Bares part: and indeed we have it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good information that there were ſuch words ſpoken; only they were the <hi>ſpectators</hi> words, and not the <hi>Actors:</hi> but this we are aſſured of, the words then ſpoken by the <hi>Actor</hi> were thoſe above mentioned, as <hi>he himſelfe</hi> acknowledged, and we find them printed ſo in the Book.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Place</hi> wherein the <hi>Play</hi> was acted, was not a <hi>Stage</hi> erected on purpoſe, but a <hi>Chamber</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:50496:7"/>to the <hi>Inne,</hi> a larg Chamber, and which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time had been a Malting roome, having a part of it covered with earth to that purpoſe. It had two Beames to ſupport it, of which one Sc: the ſhorter was a great, <hi>ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> &amp; ſubſtantiall one, &amp; lay between the two ſide walls; the other had one end ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the middle of the ſhorter beame, and the other end of it faſtned in the wall, of which you may ſee a deſcription.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>stage setup</figDesc>
               <head>The <hi>2</hi> end Walls. A. The <hi>2</hi> Beames B. The ſid-Walls C. The ſhort Beame, which broke neare the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, was betwixt <hi>13</hi> and <hi>14</hi> Inches ſquare, one end lying even, or a little within the Wall upon a ſhoulder of Stone, the other end almoſt a foot in the Wall, the ſhort Beame breaking the other fell with it.</head>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:8"/>
            <p>The fall was not very quick, but ſomewhat ſlow, &amp; gentle, in ſo much that ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thought it was a part of the play, (but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſaddeſt part) &amp; expected whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould be taken up againe, yet was it not ſo ſlowe as that they were able to recover themſelves, for the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors then in action fell down, and a great number of people with them into the under roome, which was a <hi>Shufle-board-roome,</hi> and the <hi>table</hi> it ſelfe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in peeces by the fall of the Timber. The Chamber did not fall down quite, but lay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what pendulous, and hanging, broad at the top, and narrow at the bottome, that end of the long beame, which lay in the ſhort falling down, the other end not falling, &amp; the ends of the ſhort Beame where it brake hanging down, the bottome where the people lay was of a very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſſe, the people falling as it were into a Pit: &amp; ſuch were the apprehentions of ſome of the Spectators, ſeeing the chamber ſink in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as if the <hi>earth was opening, and ſwallowing them up.</hi> After the Crack of the beame which was exceeding great, and the fall of the Chamber (in the manner as is before deſcribed) all was quiet, and ſtill, and a kind of ſilence for a pretty ſpace of time, the people being aſtonied, and bereft of their ſenſes. One that was preſent was ſo much affrighted (as was ſaid) that ſhe thought her ſelfe verily to be in Hell, which we do the rather inſert becauſe whoever ſhall put the circumſtances to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether may well ſay it was a little reſemblance of that black, and diſmall place, there being ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:50496:8"/>taken in the middeſt of their ſinfull practiſes, and thruſt into a pit together where they were left in darkneſſe, the <hi>Lights</hi> being put out by the fall, where the duſt that was raiſed made a kind of Miſt, and Smoake, where there were the moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable ſkreekes, and out-cryes that may be imagined; where they were ſhut up as in a priſon, and could not get themſelves out, (the doore of the under roome being blocked up, and their leg's being ſo pinioned, &amp; wedged together by faggots, and other things, that fell down together with them from the upper roome, that they could not ſtirre to help themſelves.) Another (as is ſaid) ſuppoſing his limbs to be all plucked aſunder cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>that they ſhould cut off his head:</hi> this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the fright was exceeding great, and many were dead for a time that afterward came to themſelves. When the people were come to themſelves, there was a fearfull, and moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cry, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e crying one thing, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e another, ſome crying <hi>aid for the Lords ſake, others crying Lord have mercy on us, Chriſt have mercy on us,</hi> others cryed oh my Huſband! a ſecond, oh my Wife! a third, Oh my child! and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid, No body loves <hi>me</hi> ſo well as to ſee where my child is. Others cryed out for Ladders, and Hatchets to make their paſſage out, for the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber falling, the doore of the under roome was ſo Blocked up that they could not get out there, ſo that they were fain to break the barres of the window, and moſt of the people got out that way though it were a good ſpace of time before
<pb facs="tcp:50496:9"/>they could get forth. The other Players that were not in action were in the Attiring-roome which was joyning to the chamber that fell, and they helped to ſave ſome of the people which were neer that part. Thoſe of the people that fell not down, but were preſerved by that meanes got out at the window of the upper roome. There were five ſlaine outright, whereof three were Boys, two of which being about ſeaven, or eight yeares old or thereabout; the other neer twelve: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two were Girles, the elder of which being fourteen, or fiveteen, and the younger twelve, or thirteen yeares old. A woman alſo had her legg ſorely broken that the ſurgeons were forced to cut it off, and ſhe dyed within three or foure dayes after it was cut off. Many were hurt, and ſorely bruiſed, to the number of about threeſcore, that we have certaine information of, beſides thoſe that conceale their greifes, and ſome of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of which there were diverſe preſent, it being market day when this Play was acted.</p>
            <p>The Surgeon that dreſſed the wounded people, told me that the next day after this was done he was counting with himſelfe how many he had dreſſed, and as neere as he could reckon he had dreſſed about fortie five, and twelve after that as he had ſuppoſed, and two or three after he had cut off the womans legg. Which therefore I thought good to inſert that the reader may know upon what grounds he may take this relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Some others were dreſſed by others in the town
<pb facs="tcp:50496:9"/>the juſt number of which I have not learn't But it is generally conceaved that there were divers did receive hurt which would not ſuffer it to be knowen. Among thoſe that were hurt there were about a dozen broken armes, and leggs, and ſome two or three diſlocations, as we were likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Surgeon. Some of the people came out with bloody faces, neither could it be otherwiſe, they having trod one upon another in a moſt ſad, and lamentable manner. Certain it is there was much hurt done that way; the children that were killed, being ſtifled as was ſuppoſed. The man in womans apparrell lay panting for breath, and had it not been for <hi>Bremo</hi> his fellow Actor, he had been ſtifled; but <hi>Bremo</hi> having recovered himſelfe a little, bare up the others head with his arme, whereby he got ſome breath, and ſo was preſerved; but both the one, and the other were hurt; <hi>Bremo</hi> being ſo ſorely bruiſed, as that he was fain to keep his bed for two dayes after, and the Lady had her beuty mar'd, her face being ſwoln by the hurt taken in the fall. Some had their mouths ſo ſtuf'd with duſt that they could hardly ſpeak, the people that came from the houſe made a pittifull moane, ſome going in the ſtreets, and complaining, here is a Play, a ſad Play indeed, others crying out to them that met them, (as they are wont that have received ſome deadly wound) oh I am kil'd! Some cryed out that their Armes were broken, others that their Leggs were broken, ſome curſed the Players that ever they came to <hi>Witny,</hi> and the players them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:50496:10"/>wiſhed that they had never came thither. They that received no hurt were exceedingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, inſomuch that one of them that were preſent, as I am credibly informed, did ſay, that he would not, for as much as <hi>Witny</hi> was worth, be in the like affright again, though he were ſure he ſhould have no hurt. Others ſaid they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver goe to a play more, and that it was a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Others have been ſo prophane; as we hear, to make a laughing-ſtock of it, and ſome ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as to ſay, they would go againe, if it were to morrow next: and too many apt to ſay it was but a chance, a misfortune, the beame was weak, there were ſo many load of people there, and the like. But how ſleight ſo ever the matter was made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, ſure enough it is, it was ſad enough then. It was one of the ſaddeſt, and blackeſt nights that ever came on <hi>Witny.</hi> Sad it was to ſee Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents carry home their Children dead in their armes, ſad it was to ſee ſo many bruiſed, hurt, and maimed, and ſome, as it were, halfe dead that were not able to help themſelves, but were fain to be carryed away by their friends, ſome on their backs, ſome on chaires, ſad it was to hear the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous cryes of thoſe that were not there bemoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their diſtreſſed friends. This was the ſad end of this ungodly play. And what was ſpoken in jeſt in the beginning of it, by the juſt hand of God, was made good in earneſt. The Comedy being turned into a Tragedy, it had a ſad <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> ending with the deaths of ſome, and hurts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. And as it was ſaid before
<pb facs="tcp:50496:10"/>
               <q>And make thee mourn where moſt thou joy'ſt</q>
            </p>
            <p>So by the juſt hand of God came it to paſſe. For in the midſt of their mirth, and jollity did this fall out, in the middeſt of theſe amorous paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Bremo,</hi> and his Lady was this ſtroke given; yea, immediately before they expected the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pleaſure, and contentment. For the Actors ſaid the beſt of the play was ſtill behind, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after the hearts, and fancyes of the Spectators were to be filled with the love-complements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Mucedorus,</hi> and his <hi>Amadine.</hi> So true was that
<q>Turning thy mirth into a deadly Dole.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord from heaven, having given a check to ſuch wanton ſports, teaching men what they muſt look for, and that he will not bear with ſuch groſſe open profaneneſſe in ſuch an age of light as this is. That he will ſo farre take notice of the Atheiſme, and profaneneſſe of men in this world, as ſhall keep the world in order, though he hath reſerved the great, and full recompence for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, and place.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50496:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50496:11"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. I. XVIII.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven againſt all ungodlineſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may ſeeme ſtrange to ſome of you to heare ſuch a text read.<note place="margin">The Preface.</note> What, is love ſo ſoone turned into wrath? The laſt time I was called to ſpeak unto you upon a Lords day, the firſt words of the text were <hi>God is love;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh 4.8.9.</note> pure love, goodneſſe, and ſweetneſſe, all love as it were, made up of love. Now the text beginnes with <hi>the wrath of God,</hi> heavy wrath, dreadfull, aſtoniſhing wrath; enough to break in pieces the hardeſt heart to heare it but ſo much as mention'd. Its the wrath of <hi>God;</hi> Its wrath <hi>from heaven,</hi> its <hi>revealed wrath,</hi> 'tis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, and declared in open ſight. This is a great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50496:12"/>change indeed may ſome one ſay to paſſe from the ſweeteſt Love to the moſt terrible and diſmall wrath. But the Lord himſelfe hath changed the text, and it is he that hath given it, by that which he hath wrought in the midſt of you, and done in the face of the whole Towne. Can you look back upon that late ſad and aſtoniſhing Providence, of which as many as heare, their eares tingle at it, their hearts ſhake and tremble at it: can you, I ſay, look upon this ſtrange &amp; wonderfull Providence, and not ſee this written in Broad and Capitall letters, and even laid before you in what is come to paſſe. <hi>That the wrath of God is revealed from heaven againſt all ungodlineſſe, and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be not prejudiced, my Brethren, doe not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take me: I am not come to grate upon your ſoares, neither to make wider your yet bleeding wounds: God foribd; no, I pitty and pray for thoſe among you, that are yet weake and infirme, beſeeching the Lord to heale them, and reſtore them, that they may live to teſtify their thankfulneſſe, and Repentance. My work is, as a poor unworthy Embaſſadour, and ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Lord, to help you to underſtand what the meaning of the Lord is; for certainly ſo great a thing could not be in vaine. <hi>The Lords voice crieth unto the citie,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Micah. 6.95 <hi>And the man of wiſdome ſhall ſee thy Name: heare ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</hi> There is a voice gone out to you of this place, and it is the Lords voice, his Name is written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what was done but the other week, this name
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50496:12"/>of his is wrirten with faire and legible characters, that he which runnes may read: this voice of his, it doth not whiſper, it doth not mutter, no, it <hi>cries,</hi> it ſpeakes aloud, it will be your wiſdome to heare this voice. Every rod hath a voice in it, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and moſt petty afflictions ſpeak ſomething from God. Great and mighty ſtrokes, eminent and remarkable Judgments from heaven, they have a loud voice, and if ſuch be not heard, they bring ſpeedy ruine.</p>
            <p>Let not any among you ſay, the Preacher is come to vent himſelfe, and his own Paſſions, and we expected ſome thundering ſermon after this: No, no, I am not come to that purpoſe, but in all humility and ſeriouſneſſe to beſeech you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what the mind of the Lord is, and I have beg'd from the Lord (as well as I could) wiſedome and direction to know what I ſhould ſpeak: be not ſuch enemies to your ſelves, and to that good the Lord intends you this day, as to ſay when you come home, we have heard a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Judgment, and that is all; we expected ſome ſuch thing. Do not ſo ill requite the Lord and his word, but har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the counſels of his word, and be obedient to the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſcope of the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle,<note place="margin">The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> is to ſet downe the true way of mens Juſtification, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; which he affirmes to be by the pure grace of God, and not by the works of men. This way, or modell of God in ſaving men, the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all principle from whence both their Juſtification and Salvation muſt ariſe, <hi>viz imputed righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50496:13"/>he calls the <hi>righteouſneſse of God</hi> in the verſe before the text, which is ſo called, becauſe the righteouſneſſe by which men are ſaved is a righteouſneſſe of Gods finding out, and of his own beſtowing, and not any ſuch thing as men have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther framed, and deviſed themſelves; or were able to work out by any thing that they could doe. This righteouſneſſe, he ſaies, is revealed in the Goſpell: it is the Goſpell that chalkes out this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, and plat-forme of righteouſneſſe and life, and by this way muſt men be juſtified and ſaved, and not by their owne workes: this is the maine propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition which he layes down in the 17 verſe. In the text we have the firſt proof, or argument to make that aſſertion good, &amp; the argument ſtands thus.</p>
            <p>The workes of all men in the world, whether Jewes or Gentiles, ever ſince the fall of Adam, they are wicked, ungodly, unrighteous workes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot be ſaved by them: the argument is very cleare, and ſtrong here. All men deſerve wrath, the utmoſt wrath, diſpleaſure, and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God by thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne workes, therefore they cannot deſerve his love, favour, or good will: they are ſo far from deſerving his love, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the quite contrary. This is the coherence.</p>
            <p>For explication of the words,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The wrath of God</hi>] By <hi>wrath,</hi> we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand wrath in the Root, and in the Fruit; in the cauſe,<note place="margin">The open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Text.</note> and in the effect. God is highly diſpleaſed with men by reaſon of ſin, he loathes their wayes and abhorres their practiſes, he beares a bitter, and a deadly hatred againſt all the wickedneſſe which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50496:13"/>men commit; and he hath an inward quarrell, (if we may ſo ſpeak) a ſecret grudge in his heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men themſelves for the ſame: this is wrath in the root, or cauſe. And then againe he inflicts plagues and puniſhments, the moſt dreadfull cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and fearfull judgments on men by reaſon of ſin; all which are viſible and ſignall tokens of his diſpleaſure, and manifeſt proofs, that he cannot endure them, nor any of their wayes: this is wrath in the fruit, or effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is revealed from heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be a twofold ſenſe of this.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Simpliciter ſignificat Pau lus, manifeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſſe quam ut quiſquam inficiari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſit, Dominum è caelo in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ac ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los homines indignari Beza.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſenſe may be, it is revealed clearly and manifeſtly, as much as if it were by a voice from heaven. The Lord God Almighty, the bleſſed and moſt holy God, he proclaimes it from heaven, and cries aloud in the eares of all the world, that he is deeply offended with all the ungodlineſſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe which men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit, that he will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly call them to an account, and puniſh them for it. In <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 14: 2. it is ſaid <hi>The Lord looked from</hi> HEAVEN <hi>upon the children of men, to ſee if there were any that did understand, and ſeek God;</hi> now here it is ſaid, his wrath is revealed <hi>from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> God is no idle ſpectator, he doth not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsly behold the actions of men, as if ſo be they might doe what they liſted, and he not diſcerne, or not be moved at it: no, he looks down from heaven <hi>upon the children of men.</hi> Jehovah from the heavens looked down upon the ſons of <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo one reads it: He looks with a watchfull obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant eye; his eye is intent and fixt upon all the ſons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50496:14"/>of <hi>Adam,</hi> upon the whole raceof mankind, and for what is all this curious ſearch made? it is <hi>to ſee if there were any that did understand and ſeek God:</hi> But was he well pleaſed when he found it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? no ſurely, finding all to be <hi>corrupt,</hi> that they were <hi>all gone aſide,</hi> that <hi>they were</hi> all together <hi>beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e filthy,</hi> that <hi>there was none that did good no not one,</hi> that they were <hi>workers of</hi> iniquity. v. 1.3.4. he gives out the ſentence, he pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth it <hi>from heaven,</hi> he proclaimes it in the eares of all the world, that he is highly offended, and his wrath is gone out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men by reaſon of theſe things. Pſalm: 4.2. <hi>O ye ſons of men how long will ye love vanity, and ſeek after leaſing?</hi> how long will ye run mad on ſin, and be ſo deſperately adventerous in the waies in which you walk? <hi>But know that the Lord hath ſet apart him that is godly for himſelfe.</hi> verſe 3: Take it for granted, that JEHOVAH, that is, the Higheſt Lord, the Majeſty of heaven and earth, he is provoked, and incenſed by all theſe waies, and it is the godly man that he lookes after: know ye, Jehovah hath marvelouſly ſeperated a gratious ſaint to him; <hi>ſo Ainſworth.</hi> It is the pious, devout, holy ſoul that Jehovah regards, and he hath marvelouſly ſeperated him, or ſelected in wondrous ſort,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>ſegregavit,</hi> Graecum, &amp; Latinum, <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificavit,</hi> quod verbum non eſt alienum a propoſito ubi bi de opilio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad regiam dignitatem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vecto agitur; ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> a, Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matica, cùm verba, quae <hi>mirabile facere &amp; ſeparare</hi> Hebraice ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant, fimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia ſint, atque idcirco ſuas fignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es facile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint ex regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, &amp; uſn Hebraicae lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae. Muis in loc.</note> he hath put him in another rank, ſet a mark of excellency upon him, he hath ſet him in oppoſition to the wicked ungodly men, and ſuch as love vanity, whome he hath ſet on another file, whoſe names are written in his black book, and hath marked them out as the objects of his wrath. this is illuſtrated <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.4: 5: <hi>ver.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50496:14"/>The Lord is in his holy temple, The Lords throne is in heaven: his eyes behold, his eye-lids tries the children of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord trieth the righteous: but the wicked, and him that loveth violence his ſoul hateth</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſenſe may be, the wrath of God is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven,</hi> that is, it is manifeſted by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, cleare, remarkable plagues, and Judgments <hi>from heaven.</hi> God hath diſcovered to all the world, that he is an utter enemy to all the ſin, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ungodlineſſe of men, becauſe he hath puniſhed in all generations wicked, and ungodly men with moſt fearfull plagues and judgments; he hath ſhewen ſignes, and tokens <hi>from heaven,</hi> ſo that all men have ſeene his hand.<note place="margin">Pareus.</note> A learned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitor underſtands this phraſe from <hi>Heaven,</hi> as that which is oppoſed to the opinion of prophane men, who aſcribe the puniſhments that are ever now and then lighting upon men, to chance, or ſecond cauſes, the poſition of the ſtarres, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of the elements, the mutability of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: whereas the Apoſtle ſhewes clearly that this wrath deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds from heaven, and is even the <hi>ſcourge</hi> and <hi>whip of God,</hi> whereby he revengeth the impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and injuſtice of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againſt all ungodlineſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe of men:</hi> by <hi>ungodlineſſe,</hi> we are to underſtand ſinnes againſt the firſt Table, all contempt of God, of religion, of the worſhip of God, of the waies and ordinances of God, the wrong and injury that is done to God himſelf more immediately, or to any part of his worſhip.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Phav.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50496:15"/>
            <p>By <hi>unrighteouſneſſe</hi> is mean't ſins againſt the ſecond Table,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Gr.</hi> Scho l. in Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 1.</note> all oppreſſion, injuſtice, riot, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; and the like.</p>
            <p>Againſt <hi>all</hi> ungodlineſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe becauſe there are ſeverall ſins comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der either head</p>
            <p>Here alſo <hi>ungodlineſſe</hi> and <hi>unrighteouſneſſe</hi> is put for perſons committing ſuch things, the Abſtract being put for the Concrete. <hi>Who hold the truth &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is added as an aggravation of the ſinne of men, that men ſin againſt light and knowledge, and therefore doe more abundantly deſerve that wrath which is reveal'd from heaven againſt them. The doctrine ariſing hence is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Bleſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine</note> 
               <hi>and moſt holy God hath all along ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, and declared his utter hatred, abhorrence, and deteſtation of all ungodly, and unrighteous perſons; and of all the ungodlineſse and unrighteousneſse which they commit: and at ſundry times hath confirm'd, and made good that diſpleaſure of his by fearfull, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Judgments inflicted on men in this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or more briefly that you may all remember it. <hi>God is certainly angry with ſin, and ſinners, and doth oftentimes in this world ſhew his diſpleaſure againſt them by remarkable Judgments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this we muſt ſhew</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. what this <hi>hatred,</hi> or <hi>wrath</hi> of God meaneth.</item>
               <item>2. Prove in a ſcripture or two, that this wrath of God ſo opened, and unfolded hath been mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to have been in God.</item>
               <item>3. how, or by what wayes, and meanes it hath been manifeſted.</item>
               <item>4. Give proof, that it hath been confirm'd by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50496:15"/>Judgments inflicted on men from time to time.</item>
               <item>5. Why God takes this courſe to manifeſt his wrath by plagues, and judgments in this world.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What is this wrath of God?</p>
            <p>It implyeth two things: the Holineſſe of his will: the Juſtice of his will.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Holineſſe of his will:</hi> the will of God is abſolutely, univerſally ſet againſt all ſin, he diſlikes it, he abhorres it, he hates it to the very death, it is that which goes againſt him, he cannot endure it, neither will he, it ſtrikes at his own bleſſedneſſe, &amp; therefore he muſt needs hate it.<note n="f" place="margin">Omne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediens à be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudine debet odiri Aquin.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Thou haſt loved righteouſneſſe, and hated iniquity.</hi> That, which a man hateth, he wiſheth the death of. God hath taken up an irreconcileable, and eternall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt ſin, it never ſtood with his holineſſe to like it, neither ever will it. Nay; he is ſo holy he cannot but hate it. The wrath of God therefore is the diſpleaſure, which he hath conceived in his heart againſt ſin, the ſecret grudge, and quarrell which he beares to every man that is a ſinner, and cannot but beare to him conſidered as ſuch, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in that eſtate.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſtot.</note> Wrath, as the Philoſophers define it, is a deſire of revenge for ſome ſeeming ſleight, or diſreſpect ſhewen to a man. As a Prince when he is diſgraced, reviled, reproched or any way ſtruck at by one of his ſubjects,<note n="h" place="margin">Sola parvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſio cauſat iram, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne provocans iram eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſub ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſti. Aquin.</note> he is preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, his blood is up,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ira eſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſtratius re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. Grot.</note> &amp; he reſolves to right him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to revenge the quarrell of his honour on ſuch a man. But God hath no ſuch paſſions, only ſo far we may ſay, the bleſſed God looks upon ſin as a ſlight, as a diſreſpect ſhewen unto him, he looks upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50496:16"/>and ſinners as contemning his holy majeſty, as ſcorning him, and ſetting him at nought, and this he hates, and cannot but hate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Phavor.</note> wrath of God implyes the <hi>juſtice</hi> of his <hi>will,</hi> the will of God hates ſin, and it is reſolved to puniſh ſin, the will of God is carried with utter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of ſin, and it will be reveng'd for ſin, it will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict puniſhment for ſin. Wrath in our ſenſe is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of revenge, when there is ſome evill inflicted proportionable to the wrong a man ſuffers, and this is properly called puniſhment.<note n="*" place="margin">Eſt autem paena genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſignificatu malum paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis quod inſtigitur ob malum ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis. Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins de jure belli &amp; pacis.</note> Now there are no paſſions in God, as was ſaid before, but thus we muſt conceive it; God reſolves to lay a meet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, a juſt reward upon men for ſin; ſin in its own nature, deſerves the heavieſt curſes, and therefore theſe are meaſured out by the juſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> jus Dei.</note> and upright will of God, as the fitteſt recompence thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the judgment of God, that they which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch things are</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ad jus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem pertinet aptitudo quam Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> id eſt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Michael Epheſius id quod ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eam ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quale dicitur interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quod convenit. Grotius de jure belli &amp; pacis.</note> 
               <hi>worthy of death. Rom.</hi> 1.32. <hi>God will render to every man according to his workes. Chap.</hi> 2.6. This is another thing that muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the wrath of God, the diſtributive juſtice of God whereby he lay's actuall plagues, and puniſhments on men according to their deſerts. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Then ſhall he ſpeak unto unto them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi> Here is wrath, and the fruit of wrath; the Lord is angry, and he makes it known that he is ſo; his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is a vexing, troubling anger, it leaves not men at eaſe in their ſinnes, but it quickly diſquiets them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50496:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Second particular for the proſecuting of the doctrine, was to inſtance in a Scripture or two, whereby it apeares that there is ſuch anger in God towards ſin, and ſinners; and to proove that there is ſuch wrath indeed, which hath been manifeſted as hanging over men by reaſon of ſin. One or two places will be enough for this. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 8.22. <hi>The hand of our God is upon all them for good that ſeek him, but his power, and his wrath is againſt all them that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him. Nahum.</hi> 1.2. <hi>God is jealous, and the Lord revengeth; the Lord revengeth, and is furious; the Lord will take vengeance on his adverſaries, and he reſerveth wrath for his enemies.</hi> The Prophet is here deſcribing the nature of God, and he beginnes with jealouſy.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Aquinas. 1ma: 2dae. Quaeſt. 28. Art. 4.</note>Jealouſy is an affection proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrength, and intenſnes of love, and that which ſtirres it up is ſomewhat that would rob a man of the quiet, and ſole enjoyment of what he deſires. God loves himſelfe and his own glory above all, and good reaſon for it, he being the higheſt and moſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme good. Sin in its proper nature, and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on goes about to rob him of what is neareſt to him and therefore no wonder if he be jealous. This jealouſy of his is manifeſted in the next wordes, <hi>The Lord revengeth, the Lord revengeth, the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vengeance.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Cum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ait Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſemper eſt in Heb: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um verum, &amp; omnipotente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi eſſe ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, qui nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins potentiâ prohiberi, aut impediri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſit. Ribera.</note> The name of Jehovah is thrice repeated in this one verſe, this he doth to ſhew that it is the true, and living God, he that is omnipotent, whoſe power and wrath none can reſiſt, that was fallen out with them, and become their enemie. And<note n="n" place="margin">Ter autem <hi>ulciſcens,</hi> ſive ultor dicitur, quod aſſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem magnam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, &amp; certiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ultio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem: etenim <hi>Ternarius</hi> magnam vim habet ad amplifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Ribera.</note> the name of vengeance is as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attributed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50496:17"/>to him, the Lord <hi>revengeth, revengeth, will take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> which ſhewes the terribleneſſe of his wrath, and the certainty of it. There are alſo two other expreſſions that ſet forth the greatneſſe, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his wrath, <hi>he is furious,</hi> or as the Margin hath it <hi>that hath fury,</hi> which beſt ſuits with the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall which hath it,<note n="o" place="margin">Dominum irae vocat, ira &amp; indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum q.d. non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunquam oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit ſe eſſe iratum, quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infligit gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves poenas. Vatabl.</note> the <hi>Lord of Anger,</hi> that is, one that is armed with wrath, and indignation againſt his enemies, &amp; ſhewes himſelf to be angry by infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting grievous puniſhments on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="p" place="margin">Ego <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> non Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer accipio pro irâ ſed pro efectu irae. Calv. in loc.</note> This is intimated in the other expreſſion, <hi>he reſerveth wrath for his enemies.</hi> The word wrath is not againe repeated in the originall, but is taken from that which went before to make the ſenſe compleat. He is the Lord of wrath, he hath plagues &amp; puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts enough at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand: theſe he reſerves &amp; keepes by him for a fit time, &amp; then, be ſure, he will execute them to the utmoſt. 3. <hi>The third Particular.</hi> By what wayes, and meanes hath this wrath of God been manifeſted to men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe two waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By naturall light. 2. By the light of the word.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the light of nature, or of conſcience. There is ſuch a power left in all mens hearts, (which is called conſcience) that upon<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sic Hie ocles in verſum.</note> ſin commited, or good omitted ſummons men to the tribunall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50496:17"/>of the ſupreme Majeſty, telling them, that they owe puniſhment to that ſoveraigne juſtice for the commiſſion of the one, and the omiſſion of the other. The Gentiles, who had nothing but the light of nature, had this court of<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. appellat idem Hieroc.</note> judicature erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>last. Who knowing the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God that they which commit ſuch things are worthy of Death &amp;c.</hi> This was a principle rivetted, and ſeated in all their hearts, this they knew full well, they<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vid. Bez. in textum.</note> acknowlegd it as true, (though they were ignorant of, and denied many other truths) that they which committed ſuch, and ſuch ſinnes were worthy of Gods <hi>wrath:</hi> for that is meant by <hi>Death,</hi> that bearing the name of <hi>death</hi> here, which is called <hi>wrath</hi> in the 18. verſe. Hence it was that many of the Heathens ſpake of a<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Plut. adv. Col.</note> golden eye, a revengefull eye, an eye of juſtice that ſaw all, and would be revenged for all the wickedneſſe, that men committed.</p>
            <p>This is farther ſet forth in that famous text; <hi>Rom</hi> 2.15. where the apoſtle ſpeaking of the Gentiles, ſayes, <hi>their conſcience alſo bearing witneſſe, and their thoughts the meane while accuſing, or els ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing one another.</hi> When they had ſin'd their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences accuſed them, and told them, this they ought not to have done, and there was one that ſaw and would take vengeance for this: the<note n="t" place="bottom">Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim ſenſus eſſe videtur, cogitationes ſe mutuò, <hi>i.e.</hi> aliam aliam accuſâſſe, aut excuſâſſe, ſed inter ſe, &amp; quaſi alternatim, aciper vices eum in quo reperiebantur prout nempe unus idem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nunc òene, nunc male ageret opera<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> virtutum ac vitiorum vices quaſdam inter ſe obtinerent, ſimiliter cogitationes inter ſe vices nunc excuſa ndi nunc accuſandi habu iſſe. <hi>Ladov. de Dieu.</hi>
               </note> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not (ſo much as the letter of the word ſeems to import) as if ſo be the thoughts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did grate one upon another, one thought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50496:18"/>it ſelf when it was good, and condemning it ſelf when it was evill: but the plainer ſenſe ſeems to be; that they had accuſing thoughts when they did evill, and excuſing thoughts when they did well; the <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>perſon</hi> acquitting, or accuſing himſelfe in his own thoughts according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of his actions, his own <hi>thoughts</hi> (which is no more then the exerciſe of conſcience) juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him when he did well, and condemning him when he did otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Moſt men, if not all, eſpecially when they fall into ſome groſſe ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Plut. de his qui ſero à nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine puniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> they have this warning, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance from Conſcience, thou haſt ſinned, &amp; thou wilt be damned for this another day. Now God by this meanes diſcovers his hatred againſt ſin, and his wrath hanging over the ſinner. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is Gods officer, it is his Herald to proclaime his wrath to men. If one Prince ſend his Herald at armes to another Prince, or a Generall of an Army ſends his challenge by drum or trumpet, there is then open warre, and all men know it. God hath ſet up this light in men by which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes open warre to them in caſe they ſin againſt him. Wouldeſt thou know whether God be angry yea or no? look within, doeſt thou feel no gripes, or prickings there? doth not thy heart ſecretly<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Idem.</note> ſink and fall after ſuch a ſin? Oh miſerable man what have I done! certainly I have brought my<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hiercel.</note> ſelf under the diſpleaſure of the Almighty. If thy conſcience be not ſtupid, or ſeared there are ſuch ſecret remembrances as theſe are:<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Idem.</note> And this is one way by which God inſtructs the ſons of men,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50496:18"/>what the nature of ſin is, and what they muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if ſo be they venture on it,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond way whereby the wrath of God is manifeſted is, the light of the word. Now this is twofold,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The light of the Law.</item>
               <item>2. The light of the Goſpell.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It is manifeſted by the light of the Law, the Law threatning nothing but death, curſes, plagues, and vengeance to all ſin, and ungodlineſſe whatſoever: <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>In the day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye. Curſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the Law to doe them. Gal.</hi> 3.10. wouldſt thou know whether the wrath of God hangs over men by reaſon of ſin, doe but read the 28. <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teron.</hi> There you ſhall find curſe upon curſe. In the 15. verſe. <hi>it is ſaid all theſe curſes ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and overtake thee. Curſed ſhalt thou be in the city, and curſed in the field, curſed ſhall be thy basket, and curſed in thy ſtore,</hi> v. 20. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſend upon thee curſing, vexation, &amp; rebuke in all that thou ſetteſt thine hand unto for to doe, untill thou be deſtroyed, and untill thou periſh quickly, becauſe of the wickedneſſe of thy doings, whereby thou hast for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me.</hi> The Law threatneth nothing but wrath: it <hi>worketh wrath. Rom.</hi> 4.15. It cauſes a ſenſe of wrath, by threatning wrath to all the tranſgreſſors of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it otherwiſe in the goſpell? no: the goſpel, that reveals wrath too. The wrath of God <hi>is revea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led from heaven.</hi> As much as if the Apoſtle ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50496:19"/>ſay: we the Apoſtles and Embaſſadours of God do bring this meſſage from heaven, and publiſh it in our goſpell to the world: that the wrath of God is due to men by reaſon of ſin: all men by nature are under wrath already, they are <hi>children of wrath Eph.</hi> 2. and there is a day which is comming, when this wrath ſhall come upon them to the utmoſt, if they doe not believe, and repent.</p>
            <p>Obj. Yea, but the goſpell reveales Chriſt, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, pardon of ſin?</p>
            <p>An. True, this is the firſt intention of the goſpell,<note place="margin">Heb, 2.3.</note> and the firſt offer which it makes: but if men <hi>neglect ſo great ſalvation,</hi> if they will not ſtoop to goſpell tearms, and ſubmit to what it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, if they will not <hi>repent, and believe,</hi> then there is ſo much the more wrath,<note place="margin">Mark 1.14.15.</note> and the heavyer vengeance <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28.29. <hi>He that deſpiſed Moſes Law, died without mercy, under two or three witneſſes. Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath troden under foot the ſonne of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the goſpell teacheth, that God will judge the ſecrets of mens hearts. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>In the day when God ſhall judge the hearts of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpell.</hi> Thy ſecret pride, covetouſneſſe, ambition, thy ſecret thefts, adulteries, thy ſecret ſcorning of the word and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; theſe muſt be all judged, the Goſpell that hath ſaid ſo much in effect. It is according to the Doctrine of the goſpell, that there muſt a generall judgment paſſe on all a mans ſinnes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on the ſecrets of their hearts, his inward, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50496:19"/>moſt ſecret ſins. It is according to <hi>my goſpell,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, that men muſt be judged: why, where had <hi>Paul ſaid ſo?</hi> In that ſamous ſermon of his: <hi>Acts:</hi> 17.30.31. <hi>And the times of this ignorance God winked at, but now commandeth all men every where to repent: becauſe he hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the world in righteouſneſſe by that man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Dead.</hi> Or elſe he ſaies according to <hi>his goſpell,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this was the tenor of the goſpell, a part and portion of the goſpell, one of the moſt ordinary and uſuall Doctrines therein revealed, he, and the reſt of the Apoſtles going up and down, and preaching the day of judgment unto men, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that as a maine argument why they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and believe; becauſe that there was a day a comming, when they muſt be called to a reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for all their ſinnes. So likewiſe it is the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell that ſaies 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.8.9. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhal be revealed from heaven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, takeing vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the goſpell of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Part.</note> The fourth thing for the proſecution of the Doctrine was, to make proof that this wrath of God towards ſin, and ſinners hath been confirmed, and made good by ſundry judgments inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinners from time to time. Now here we need not ſtand long, the whole Book of God is full of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50496:20"/>cleare, and pregnant examples to this purpoſe. You all know the ſtory of the old world: it is ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly, God brought <hi>in the flood upon the world of the ungodly.</hi> 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.5. You have all read, or heard the judgment that befell <hi>Sodom, and Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah:</hi> It is recorded with a ſpeciall note, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19 24. <hi>Then the Lord rained upon Sodom, and Gomorrah brimſtone, and fire from the Lord out of heaven.</hi> The name of the Lord is uſed twice here, to ſhew, that it was a ſpeciall hand from heaven that brought this.<note n="e" place="margin">Hebraiſmus eſt, pluit Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino de coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, pro Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus pluit a ſe de coelo. <hi>Vatab.</hi>
               </note> The Lord did this by himſelfe, as it were: it was not a chance, or accident; (as ſome call the moſt fearfull judgments that ever have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted) it was not the ill Craſis, and diſpoſition of ſecond cauſes, no, it was an immediate hand from heaven, it was Jehovah that did it.</p>
            <p>We might inſtance in the examples of<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, which were drowned in the red ſea in the examples of<note n="g" place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Korah, Dathan, Abiram,</hi> of<note n="h" place="margin">Iſai 37.</note> 
               <hi>Senacherib,</hi> and diverſe others.</p>
            <p>From the old Teſtament we might paſſe to the New, and ſpeak of the ends of <hi>Judas; Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira; Herod.</hi> Theſe things you all know, much alſo might be fetched from Hiſtories ſacred, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane to conſirme this. Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories are full of examples in this kind. M. <hi>Fox</hi> in his Book of Martyrs hath a ſpeciall tract to ſhew the fearfull ends of ſeverall of the moſt Eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of the Church, and people of God.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5 Partic.</note> The Laſt thing for the clearing of the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is to ſhew the grounds, and reaſons of this, why God takes this courſe many times in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50496:20"/>this world to inflict upon notorious ſinners ſome remarkable judgments: might it not be thought ſufficient, that there are eternall puniſhments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for them? The reaſons therefore why God doth this are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Reaſon 1.</note> He doth it to put a ſtop to the Atheiſme that is in the world. <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart there is no God. Pſal.</hi> 14.1. The Atheiſt ſayes, we may doe as we liſt, the Lord ſees not, neither doth he conſider; good, and evill are all one to him, and he regards it not: or as they which are deſcribed in <hi>Job. chap.</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 14.15. <hi>They ſay unto God, depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies. what is the almighty that we ſhould ſerve him? and what profit ſhould we have if we pray unto him?</hi> Now, when men are come to this paſſe, he will make them acknowledge him, whether they will or no. The Lord is marvelous patient, and long-ſuffering, he knowes how to right himſelfe, and to be even with the ſinner in the end: but if men will breake all bounds, if they will deny the majeſty above, if they will ſoff at his word, and make a mock of ſin, if they will pluck up all religion by the very roots: he will not, he cannot any longer endure it, it ſtands him upon to keep up his authority in the world, he will be own'd, and acknowledged as God among his creatures. If nothing elſe will make the proud, &amp; ſturdy hearts of men to ſtoop, and yeeld to him, his Judgments ſhall <hi>Pſal</hi> 46.10. <hi>Be ſtill, and know that I am God.</hi> It is the voice of the Lord to the proud ones of the world. It ſeems they would not know that there was a God, or at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50496:21"/>leaſt that the God of Iſrael was he, that was the true God; therefore was it that they were ſo mad againſt his people, <hi>v.</hi> 6. the <hi>Heathen raged:</hi> but, what is the next newes that we heare? <hi>He uttered his voice; the earth melted.</hi> As proud, and as ſtout as they are, no ſooner doth <hi>He</hi> ſpeak, but their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits flag, &amp; faint; thoſe great, and mighty ones who feared none, and car'd for none, they became as dead men: <hi>he</hi> uttered his voice, or as ſome read it he <hi>gave his voice.</hi> Who is this <hi>He?</hi> look back upon the former verſe, and you will quickly ſee, 'tis <hi>God</hi> that utters his voice. No ſooner doth God ſpeak a word, but their hearts faile them. Let <hi>him</hi> but ſhew himſelfe, of whom they made a mock but a little before, and queſtion'd whether there was any ſuch one, and then they feare, and tremble; they ſhrinke, and dare not hold up their heads. And why doth the Lord doe all this? Why doth he drive them to ſuch a ſtand? The end is ſet down at the 11. verſe. He will be known as God, amongſt the worſt of men. <hi>Be still, and know that I am God,</hi> and then it followes, <hi>I will be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the heathen, I will be exalted in the earth.</hi> That wicked Pharaoh, one of the worſt of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who blaſphe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed againſt heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſaid, <hi>who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his voice to let Iſrael goe? I know not the Lord, neither wil I let Iſrael goe. Exod.</hi> 5.2. This bold, this proud wretch, after he had ſeene the hand of the Lord lifted up, and felt his plagues, he is forced to know who the Lord was, and to let Iſrael goe.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2 Reaſon.</note> The Lord doth this to render men in excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50496:21"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. Therefore thou art <hi>inexcuſable O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt. Judgeſt,</hi> how is that? that judgeſt men worthy of death by ſin: that was Gods verdict, and ſentence touching ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and this all men knew by the light of nature, and had the ſame judgement and apprehention of it in themſeves: as it is c. 1. v. 32 when as a man knowes by the light, and checks of his own conſcience, that the wrath of God is due unto him by reaſon of ſin, when he ſees all the curſes that are revealed in the Law, and the fearfull ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance denounced in the goſpell againſt all unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, and unrepenting ſinners, this makes him greatly inexcuſable: but when he ſhall ſee the judgments of God executed before his eyes, and many of the ſame ranck, and kind of ſinners ſtruck dead in the midſt of their abominations, if yet he goe on in the ſame ſins, this makes him beyond meaſure inexcuſable. If a man ſhould ſee an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred theeves, or robbers hung up one after another at ſeverall aſſiſes, and yet after this, this man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould play the theefe, who would pity that man if he came to the ſame end? he knowes thee. very to be an unwarrantable, &amp; dangerous thing, the law if againſt it, and many have been puniſhed for it from time to time before his eyes, this makes him inexcuſable: ſo it is in this caſe: If God take other men in the midſt of their ſins, if he take them in the midſt of their drinking, quaffing, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſing, as he did Belſhazzar in the midſt of his cups, or ſtrike them with ſome ſecret, and ſudden blow in the midſt of their chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toneſſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50496:22"/>as he did the young man in the proverbs, who when he went to the harlots houſe, <hi>had a dart ſtruck through his liver.</hi> Chap. 7.23. or by an immediate hand from heaven, and an Angell ſent to that purpoſe, ſhall puniſh them in the midſt of their pride, tyranny, and perſecution, as he dealt with Herod. If after all this, when a man hath ſeen ſuch cleare, and manifeſt Judgments from heaven, on the perſons of others, he ſhall live in the ſame, or worſe ſins; if he ſhall continue a drunkard, an adulterer, a perſecutor, and oppoſer of the ſaints, and of religion after all this, who can ſay this man is not juſtly puniſhed? The word is plaine, and expreſſe againſt ſuch, and ſuch ſinnes; the end and iſſue of them is there revealed, and the judgments of God have ratifyed it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it; this man is left without all excuſe. <hi>Now God will have every mouth to be ſtopped; and all the world become guilty before God. Rom.</hi> 3.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Reaſ. 3.</note> The Lord inflicts judgments upon ſome, that they might be for examples unto others. 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Turning the citties of ſodom, and Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah into aſhes, condemning them with an overthrow, makeing them an enſample unto thoſe that after ſhould live ungodly.</hi> Here is both the judgment, and the reaſon of it expreſſed. <hi>He turned them into aſhes; and he condemned them with an overthrow:</hi> he had condemned their wickedneſſe before in his owne thoughs, and adjudg'd them worthy of ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere plague,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Phav.</note> and that plague muſt be nothing leſſe then a totall deſtruction, a totall overthrow; he would ſo deſtroy them as to make an utter end
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50496:22"/>of them: for that is the meaning of the word. And why would he do ſo? it was to <hi>make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an example;</hi> he ſet them up as an example, he had prepar'd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for an example in his own thoughts before, he had fitted, and deſigned them for it; now this is the edition, and ſetting forth as it were, of what he had fram'd, and contriv'd before. <hi>Saint Peter</hi> had men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned two great editions of the wrath of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, one was in the Angels that fell: He caſt <hi>them down to hell,</hi> v. 4. Here was wrath indeed. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was in the old world. He brought in the floud upon a whole world. v. 5. here was the ſecond great edition of his wrath, if I may ſo ſpeak. And the third was in that of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gommorah,</hi> theſe he<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſtituit. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ez.</hi> pone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Vulg.</hi>
               </note> conſtituted, &amp; framed for <hi>an</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heſych.</note> 
               <hi>example;</hi> that is, for a ſigne, a token, a ſure, a ſtanding remembrance of what he meant to doe with others in the like kind: <hi>And therefore is it ſaid, unto thoſe that</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ph. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heſ.</note> 
               <hi>after ſhould live ungodly.</hi> If any had a mind after this to play the Atheiſts, to caſt off all the thoughts of God, of religion, and to riot it in their luſts, as the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> they might here ſee as in a map, what their doome was like to bee. S. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons up a whole Catalogue of Judgments which befell the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. It is ſaid, <hi>now all theſe things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to them for enſamples.</hi> the meaning is not that thoſe Judgments came by chance upon them for how could they then be intended as examples, as he ſaies they were. Neither doth he ſay <hi>diviſim,</hi> and a part, that theſe things <hi>happened,</hi> and <hi>were examples,</hi> but he ſpeaks <hi>conjunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im,</hi> knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them up both in one ſentence, they happened
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50496:23"/>as examples, or for examples, that is, thoſe things which corrupt, and carnall hearts look upon as chances, and misfortunes, he in the courſe of his providence orders that they ſhould come to paſſe, that they might be examples, therefore in the 6. verſe it is ſaid, theſe things were our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, or they were<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> made our examples, being ordained, and appointed of him ſo to be. <hi>Examples</hi>] that is patterns,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Phav.</note> ſamplers, and ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, of what he intended to doe in after times. Theſe were ſome of the firſt draughts, and cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of his judgments, that men might ſee, as he had begun, ſo he intended to goe on and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are ſaid to be examples, <hi>written for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, or admonition. Examples</hi> they were ſo in their primitive intendment: and they are <hi>written</hi> too, left upon record, that <hi>we</hi> might take warning by them <hi>on whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> The laſt age of this world is like to be the worſt, and therefore is it ſaid, <hi>in the laſt dayes perilous times ſhall come,</hi> for there ſhall be ſinners of ſuch and ſuch a ſort,. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. Now God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for this before hand, he hath given many noteable examples of his judgments in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which men, if they were wiſe, would hide in their hearts, and keep ever by them; and that was his end in makeing ſuch examples, that they might be for <hi>admonition:</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Admonitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: pretioſum vocabulum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur rectis monitis mens quaſi prius emota ſuo loco reſtitui, vel antea fluctuans componi. <hi>Eez. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10</note> a pretious word (as one calls it) ſignifying the bringing of the mind back to it ſelfe againeby ſome wholeſome rebuke or other, that was formerly out of its place; or els it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſetling of the mind, that before was fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50496:23"/>and wavering. All men are apt to think ſleightly of ſin, they look upon ſin, as a harmleſſe thing, that hath no venome, nor ſting in it, they play and dally with it, as little children would do with a Snake. All this while the underſtanding is a ſleep, the mind is out of its place, it judges not of things according to the nature of them. But when the Lord from heaven beginnes to ſhoot his arrowes, when they ſee men taken in the midſt of their impieties, and puniſhed with ſome grievous, and fearfull judgments, then the mind beginnes to be awakened, and a mans thoughts begin to recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect themſelves, certainly ſin is not ſuch a trifle, it is not a toy, an empty notion, as the moſt of men doe make it. Theſe are the warnigs of God to men: his judgments executed in the world, are as ſo many monu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ents, ſtanding remembrances of his diſpleaſure againſt ſin. This is the laſt reaſon of the point.</p>
            <p>The Application followes.</p>
            <p>The firſt vſe may be a word of Terror, &amp; it is able to ſhake the heart of every unrepentant ſinner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven. Is there ſuch wrath in God as hath been opened? hath it been all along manifeſted and revealed? have his judgments confirmed it? this may ſtrike a dampe, a terror on the heart of every wretched, unrepenting ſinner in the world. Here thou mayeſt ſee what thy caſe is, and what thy doome will certainly bee: the wrath of the great God, the God of heaven, and earth is kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, it burneth, and waxes hot againſt thee, yea it will one day conſume thee, and deſtroy thee:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50496:24"/>it will tumble theeodwn into endleſſe, eaſeleſſe, &amp; remedileſſe torments. This were enough to ſhake the proudeſt Nimrods of the world, and to make the moſt ſtout hearted ſinner tremble like an <hi>aſpen leafe,</hi> would he but conſider it. The caſe is plaine, and cleare: the judgment ſure and certaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The wrath of God is revealed from heaven,</hi> its a plaine, a manifeſt thing, its written with a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beame, and there needs be no queſtion of it, thine owne conſcience, that araignes, accuſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes thee: its the voice and cry of conſcience, if thou lyeſt in ſuch, and ſuch abominations, thou muſt be damned, the word ſayes it, the Law hath pronounced it a thouſand times over and over, the goſpell that ratifyes, and confirmes it, and the judgments of God executed in the world, they put it out of doubt.</p>
            <p>Oh miſerable man or woman, who ever thou bee, be thou young or old, rich or poore, be thy rank or condition whatſoever it be, that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in thy ſecret thefts, adulteries, oaths, propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the ſabbath, whoſe heart riſeth at God, and his waies, that loveſt thy ignorance, wordli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or what ever ſin it bee, that I cannot name in which thou liveſt, and art reſolved ſo to doe! Oh miſerable, forlorne creature! The God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth is ſet againſt thee, the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp; earth is reſolved to plague &amp; puniſh thee.</p>
            <p>Art thou able to dwell with everlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, or to ſtand before a devouring fire? Art thou a fit match for the Almighty? canſt thou grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with thy maker? art thou ſtrong enough to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50496:24"/>his Almightyneſſe? What is become of all the mighty ſinners in the world? what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the world of the ungodly? Were they not all ſwllowed up together, and devoured as in a moment? What is become of the wicked So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites? Were they not conſumed with fire and brim-ſtone? Nay, thats not all, they <hi>ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 5.7.</note> they lye flaming in the fire of hell, and are ſcorched with the wrath of God there for ever. What is become of <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and all the rabble of the ungodly? Hath not this wrath of the Lord lighted on them, and are they not for ever miſerable this is thy doome &amp; portion alſo, who continueſt in thine abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Tophet is ordained of old: yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 30.33.</note> 
               <hi>for the King it is prepared, he hath made it deep, and large: the the pile thereof is fire, and much wood; the breath of the Lord, like a ſtreame of brimſtone, doth kindle it.</hi> There is elbow roome enough in hell for all the drunkards, ſwearers, Atheiſts in the world. <hi>He hath made it deepe, and large,</hi> it will hold them all, there is no feare of it: this is the place prepared for thee. Be thou a great ſinner, or little ſinner, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not, if ſo be thou be an unrepenting ſinner, it may be thy ſin is ſoe ſecret way of u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> juſt gain, it may be it is wilfull ignorance, conſtant neglect of holy duties, be it what it will be, if thou be an unrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſinner, if thou keep thy ſin in thy boſome, if thou hide it as a ſweet morſell under thy tongue, the wrath of the Lord is gone out againſt thee. Oh how great, how dreadfull is that wrath? <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>The Lord is the true God, he is the liveing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50496:25"/>God, and an everlaſting King: at his wrath the earth ſhall tremble: and the nations ſhall not be able to abide his indignation. Revel.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>And the heaven departed as a ſcrole, when it is rolled together, &amp; every mountain &amp; Iſland were moved out of their places: And the Kings of the earth, and the great men, &amp; the rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the chiefe captaines, &amp; the mighty men, and every bond-man, and every free-man hid themſelves in the dens, and in the rocks of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, And ſaid to the mountaines, and rocks fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb: For the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to stand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou mayeſt mock at the word now, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the meſſengers of the Lord, and make a light matter of ſin, hell, wrath, and judgment, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch thing. Yea but then ſhalt thou cry to the rocks, &amp; mountaines to fall on thee, &amp; to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee from the wrath of the Lord, and the ſierceneſſe of his anger. <hi>The wrath of the King is as the roaring of a Lyon,</hi> but what is the wrath of the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords? when the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſhall ſtrech forth his owne hand againſt a poore rebellious creature, one that had wallowed in his filthineſſe, and took his ſwinge in his baſe, and ſwiniſh luſts, and he ſhall ſet his owne almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyneſſe on worke to make him miferable, Oh how great muſt that miſery bee! <hi>Revelation</hi> 1.7. <hi>Behold He commeth, and every eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> all kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of the earth ſhal wail becauſe of <hi>him.</hi> There is a mighty emphaſis lies on it, it is <hi>he</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50496:25"/>who is that? look back at the 5. verſe, and you will ſee it is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the faithfull witneſſe, the firſt begotten of the dead, the prince of the Kings of the earth,</hi> unto whom <hi>glory, and dominion</hi> is due for ever and ever. <hi>Behold he</hi> commeth it is uſhered in with a note of aſtoniſhment and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement: it is not a poore deſpiſed Chriſt, it is not a carpenters ſonne that now appeares, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not in that meane, low, &amp; abject way as once he did; no, it is the glorious Lord Jeſus, it is the the faithfull witneſſe, one that hath received pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique teſtimony in heaven of his truth and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe in his fathers worke, it is he that was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by the glory of the Father, whom he hath ſet at his owne right hand, <hi>Far above all principality and powers, and might and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this world, but alſo in that which is to come.</hi> 'Tis <hi>he</hi> commeth, he comes not in a poore meane and abject manner, no he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with clouds, he ſhall come <hi>in the glory of his father,</hi> and all <hi>the holy Angells with him. Behold he commeth.</hi> Or elſe we may refer this to the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſe. v. 8. I am Alpha and Omega, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning &amp; the ending ſaith the Lord, which is, &amp; which was, &amp; which is to come; the Almighty. It is that Eternall, that Almighty one. Behold he come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. So in the Epiſtle of Jude v. 14. <hi>Behold the Lord commeth.</hi> Here we have a <hi>behold</hi> too. <hi>The Lord commeth with ten-thouſands of his Saints.</hi> To ſee ten thouſand Saints, and thouſand thouſandes of Angells comming to Judgment, Oh what a dreadfull ſight would this bee! but it is the Lord
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50496:26"/>that commeth in the front, and head of theſe, they are but his followers &amp; attendants. The <hi>Lord</hi>] he whom thou haſt hated, ſcorned, oppoſed all this while, it is the Lord that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands thou haſt made bold withall, and regarded no more then the duſt under thy feet. The Lord commeth to <hi>execute vengeance v.</hi> 15. who ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely thou ſhouldſt not be drunken, riotous, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, abuſe his mercies and the like: this glorious mighty Lord, he himſelfe commeth, he whom thou haſt diſhonoured, provoked, blaſphemed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares together, and yet he let thee alone, but now thou ſhalt pay for all, he comes to <hi>execute judgement upon all, and to convince all that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly amongſt them,</hi> he will ſpare none, high nor low, rich nor poore, all ſhall ſtand before the judgement ſeat. But is that all, it followes, <hi>he will convince them of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungodly committed.</hi> Thou canſt be tipſy in a corner, and commit filthineſſe in ſecret, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſome hidden cloſe haunts of ſin which are remote from the eyes of men, but thou ſhalt not carry it ſo, <hi>the Lord will convince all that are ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among them,</hi> as ſubtill, and as cunning an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite as thou art, thou ſhalt be unmaſked, the Lord will lay thee open before men, and Angells, thy baſeneſſe, and underhand dealing, thy dodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and dawbing in matters of religion ſhall be brought to light at that day. Thou ſayeſt as thoſe mockers did, wher is the promiſe of his comming? What is this day of Judgment, hell, and wrath that miniſters tell us ſo much off? Tuſh theſe are but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50496:26"/>Bug-beares to fright little children with; and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are grown ſo proud now a daies as they will have all men come to their bowes, and have an awe, and reverence of them: but let us not be ſo weak to hearken to ſuch tales. But what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? He will convince them <hi>of all their hard ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him.</hi> Alas! for thee poore man. It is not the miniſter thou ſpeakeſt againſt, thoſe thy wicked, thy accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, thy hard ſpeeches, they are <hi>againſt him.</hi> The Lord will not be mocked, neither will he ſuffer his creatures to laugh him to ſcorne. He will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thee one day, that ſin, hell, and wrath are not dreames, fancies, and idle tales, &amp; when thou haſt lyen ſome millions of yeares in thoſe inſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable torments, and haſt <hi>eternity, for ever</hi> lying before thee to think what thou haſt ſtill to endure, then thou wilt ſee, whether ſin be ſin, yea, or no, whether the wrath of God be a rediculous thing yea or no. Oh feare and tremble at the thoughts of theſe things: that which hath been ſaid might make the heart of every unrepentant ſinner ſhake, and his joynts to tremble. This is the firſt uſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe, and all the uſe in the generall, that ſhall be made of the point in hand,<note place="margin">Uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to Repentance: Is the wrath of God gone out againſt all the ungodlineſſe and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of men? Oh Repent, Repent betimes, ere this wrath come upon you. I have lately ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted you to repentance, by the mercies of God, by his love and goodneſſe, and the ſweet proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50496:27"/>that he hath made, he hath raiſed up his ſon the Lord Jeſus to give that bleſſing to you. You need not ſay the work is too hard, it is a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for us to repent. You have heard where your ſtrength lies: I muſt now goe another way to worke, and exhort you to repentance by the Judgments of the Lord, the text which I am hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling calls for it, and the providences of the Lord, they call for it alſo. <hi>Knowing the terror of the Lord we perſwade men,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: ſo muſt we do likewiſe. Let me ſpeak to every ſoul of you that belongs to this place, be thy rank, or condition whatſoever it bee, be thou in higher or meaner place, Repent, and that ſpeedily before the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Lord come upon you to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. I remember what John Baptiſt ſaid to the Phariſees, and Sadduces that came to his baptiſme: it may bee looked upon as a kind of argument to preſſe the doctrine of repentance more cloſely on them, <hi>Math.</hi> 3.7. <hi>who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come.</hi> I may ſay concerning you of this place, the wrath of God is already come, it hath already appeared, it is revealed from heaven in the face of the open ſun, that all that paſſe by you cannot but take notice of it. Oh repent, repent, leſt this wrath come upon you to the uttermoſt: <hi>Luke</hi> 13:4.5 <hi>Suppoſe yee thoſe eighteene upon whom the tower in Siloam fell &amp; ſlew them, thinke yee that they were ſinners aboue all men that dwell in Jeruſalem, I tell you nay: but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> He doth not ſay that they which ſuffered thoſe things were no ſinners at all,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50496:27"/>or that they were little ſinners, but he would not have them that eſcaped <hi>that</hi> danger put off the buſineſſe from themſelves, as if ſo be they that were ſlaine, and made the immediate examples of Gods diſpleaſure, were the onely ſinners in Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: no, he tels <hi>them, their</hi> ſins might be as great as any of the reſt; and therefore he adviſes them to look about themſelves, for unleſſe they repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they likewiſe ſhould periſh. Do not thinke my bretheren, that the poore children that were cruſhed to death, the men and women that had their armes and legs broken, or diſioynted, their bodyes ſorely bruiſed were ſinners above all the people in <hi>Witney,</hi> or that there are no other ſinners but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt you. Nay I tell you all, except yee repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh. Vnleſſe thou, ô man, or woman, who ever thou art, repent of thy drunkenneſſe, lying, covetuouſneſſe, of thy cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and indifferency in religion thou ſhalt one day periſh, the word ſaies it, conſcience tels thee ſo, the damned in Hell they feele it to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Oh what a ſtrange paſſe are men come unto! the wrath of God is revealed from heaven, and yet they will not believe. God hath teſtifyed it from heaven, that every drunkard, and ſwearer, and prophane perſon ſhall certainly be damned; and yet men will not believe. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Know ye not that the unrighteous,</hi> &amp;c. why, This is a plaine thing, an evident, a manifeſt thing, a man may ſay it is dark at noone day, if he will, but this is cleare and beyond all doubt it ſelfe. <hi>Know ye not that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50496:28"/>ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God.</hi> The gate of heaven ſhall never be opened to any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſoule, no uncleane thing ſhall ever enter there. No, if the holy, and righteous God be in heaven-thou which art an unholy and an unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoul ſhalt never get there; and if the Saints and Angells ſtay in heaven, thou which art ſo unlike them ſhalt never come there. Oh think on this for the Lords ſake. <hi>From heaven</hi> thou art pointed out to deſtruction, all the <hi>leaves</hi> in the Bible make againſt thee, all the Judgments that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God hath executed are cleare and plaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eyes, and yet men will not believe! What will become of this Atheiſticall generation? There is no man feares, there is no man conſiders his way. Though the bleſſed God from heaven tell men that their ungodlineſſe &amp; unrighteouſnes doth bring his wrath upon them, &amp; wil damne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the end, they wil not believe it, they will not lay it to heart. The word that threatneth wrath, the Judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, they reveale &amp; make known this wrath, the devils in hell they believe &amp; tremble at it, &amp; the damn'd, they feel it, &amp; yet the ſtout heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſonnes of men they care not for it. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Do we provoke the Lord to jealouſy, are we ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then he?</hi> Do we incenſe,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pha.</note> exaſperate, and put the Lord himſelfe to it to ſhew what he can do? are we content the Lord ſhould doe his worſt? doe we<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch.</note> equall and compare our ſelves with him? dare we juſtle, and contend with him for maſtery? Oh fearefull! are you come to this point? let the Lord do his worſt, we ſhall deale with him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50496:28"/>and his wrath well enough. Oh deſperate forlorn man! <hi>It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> Oh repent, repent.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note> It was one of the dying words of a famous Martyr. Repent O England, repent, repent, ſo ſay I to you, <hi>O Witney,</hi> repent, repent, otherwiſe I feare ſome more dreadfull plagues will befall you. You that have ungodly neighbours, ſervants, or friends go to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; aſk them, what meane you to lie in your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, prophaneneſſe, neglect of God and holy things ſtill? What do you love to be damned? and are you well pleaſed to be ſent packing to hell as ſoone as you dye? For the Lords ſake ſet upon this work ſpeedily, if you do not I feare ſome worſe thing will come next. Certainely, my Brethren, the hand of the Lord is gone out againſt you in this late Tragedy; (for ſo it ſhould be called it was not a Comedy, no, no, it was a Tragedy, a dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Play, it had a dolefull end, a bloudy, a ſad end. Thoſe of you that heard the ſcreekings and bitter complaints, the fearfull heart-piercing cries, that ſaw the broken bones, the diſioynted armes, the dead carcaſſes of ſo many children, will ſay it was a Tragedy indeed, a dolefull play) and the wrath of God hath been revealed from heaven, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven againſt thee O <hi>Witny.</hi> If there be any mockers or ſcoffers in the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are come to deride the word, I ſay if there be any ſuch, though I hope better things of the moſt of you, yet if there be any ſecret ſcoffer in a corner, I ſhall ſay to him as Job did to his friends, when
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50496:29"/>they had made light of his calamity, and ſaid, it was juſt. <hi>Job.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Suffer me that I may ſpeake, and after that I have ſpoken, mock on.</hi> You that make ſo light of the hand of God, &amp; laugh at all his judgements, heare the meſſage which the Lord ſent, &amp; if after that ye have a mind to mock, then mock ye on, take your fill of laughter, and it may be you may have your belly full of mocking ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day.</p>
            <p>Brethren, miſtake me not, my aime is not to make you ſad, (though it is fit, indeed, you ſhould be humbled for your ſins.) Alas, what pleaſure can it be to the proor ſervants, and meſſengers of the Lord to make any one ſad? No, no, it is your good, and happineſſe, it is the welfare and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this place I aime at, and I hope by that time you have heard all I have to ſay, you will be convinced, that it is ſo indeed. Let me ſpeak to you as the Apoſtle doth to his Corinthians. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Would to God you could bare with me a little in my folly, and indeed beare with me.</hi> And then at the 20 verſe. <hi>for ye ſuffer, if a man bring you into bondage, if a man devoure you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt himſelfe, if a man ſmite you on the face.</hi> Many, I feare, are apt to plead for their luſts and corruptions, for their games and ſports, which have devoured them, and conſumed them, and brought them low, and is there not as much reaſon they ſhould beare with the word which comes in all plainneſſe, and faithfulneſſe to doe them good? Certainly my brethren the hand of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50496:29"/>the Lord is lifted up, the great and dreadfull God, the King of the whole earth hath ſhewen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the midſt of you. I could have hoped there would not be found a man in this place, that was come to that height of Atheiſme, as to ſay, this not was the hand of God, this was not a judgement, it was only a chance, a miſ-fortune, &amp; ſuch a thinge might fall out, the houſe was weak, the beam was not ſtrong enough to ſupport ſuch a multitude. I could here ceaſe ſpeaking to ſuch a man, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a corner to turne aſide &amp; weep in, &amp; even pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er out rivers of teares in his behalf. It was that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> made the Prophet cry out in the like caſe. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.11. <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee.</hi> How was the Lords hand lifted up? Do but read the former verſes and you will find, in the 9. verſe we heare of his judgements being abroad, and in the 10. verſe, we heare of favour ſhewen to the wicked. <hi>Let favour be ſhewen to the wicked, yet will he not learne righteouſneſſe.</hi> The Lords hand was lifted up in a way of judgment, and in a way of mercy, it was his righteous judgment that ſome were cut off, and it was his mercy that others were ſpared, and yet when his hand was lifted up ſo Emenently, they would not ſee. The Lord hath ſhewen both his ſeverity, and his goodneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, ſeverity to them that ſufferred, and goodneſſe to you that were preſerved. Is it not the Lords goodneſſe? or to returne to the Prophets expreſſion, is it not a <hi>favour</hi> ſhewen to thee, that thou haſt thy life giventhee, when others were
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50496:30"/>cruſhed to death? is it not a favour that thou art ſafe and ſound, when others had their limbes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, their bodies grievouſly bruiſed? Oh this was that which ſo moved the Prophet, or the church her ſelfe that is brought in ſpeaking in that chapt. that ſhe knew not well how to beare it. <hi>Lord when thy hand is lifted up they will not ſee.</hi> It is a pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſpeech, and it ſavours of ſomewhat a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and troubled ſpirit. Oh the hard-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the pride and ſtoutneſſe that is in men, not to ſee when the Lords hand is ſo lifted up. What is thy heart flint, and thy Bowels made of braſſe? will not wrath from heaven, great wrath affect thee? Read what followes in the ſame verſe. <hi>They will not ſee, but they ſhall ſee.</hi> Thou winkeſt with thine eyes now, but the Lord will open them at laſt, thou wilt not believe this is the wrath of God, thou wilt believe it to purpoſe another day, and it may be that day is not far off. That I may ſhew you the wretchedneſſe of this diſpoſition, not to ſee and acknowledge the Lord in ſuch great things, but to lay them upon chance, misfortune ſecond cauſes, and the like. Conſider, 1 This is a meer heatheniſh temper, the Heathens could not do worſe then ſo, the Philiſtines they ſaid if the matter fell not out ſo and ſo, as they had caſt it, it was not the hand of the Lord that ſmote them, <hi>but it was a chance that happened.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.9. ſhall we make our ſelves Philiſtines? ſhall we compare our ſelves with the worſt of the heathens? Nay, ſome of the heathens have acknowledged the<note n="r" place="margin">Vide Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium Phyſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. Stoic. l. <hi>1.</hi> Diſſert. undecimá et ſeq. Arrian. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>12 <hi rend="sup">mo</hi>
                  </hi> Jamblich. de vitâ Pythag. cap. <hi>28.</hi> Stobaeum Eclog. Phyſic. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50496:30"/>Providence of God in ſuch<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hiero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. in aur. carm. paulo poſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> matters,<note n="t" place="margin">Nec Homerus hoc neſcivit: qui de Graecis adflictis cauſam reddit. — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lipſ. diſſ. <hi>16.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eurip. apud S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obaeum in Phyſ.</note> they lookt upon evills befalling them as the juſt puniſhments of their ſinnes, they have feared and trembled at the things that have come to paſſe, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging a Divine Power that was the cauſe of them.<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hieroc. in Aur. Car.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The<note n="x" place="margin">Circa reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> talem accepim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Tomtrua &amp; ſulgura pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rmius e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>paveſcchat <hi>Suct. in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Roman Emperours, yea thoſe among them who have been moſt<note n="y" place="margin">Auſus interdum non ſolum vultum attollere: ſed etiam <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Refert. Caſaub. de Caligula ex Dione.</hi>
               </note> prophane &amp; wicked, and at ſometimes have contemned God, religion it ſelfe, and have lookt the judgments of God in the face, with pride, &amp; ſcorne, at other times they have been ſurprized with a Panick feare. If they heard
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50496:31"/>but<note n="z" place="margin">Nam qui De os tanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneret, ad minima to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitrna &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, caput obvolvere, advero ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jora prori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere ſe eſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſub lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> condere ſolebat. <hi>Sue: Calig.</hi>
               </note> thundering, &amp; lightning, they would croutch under their bedds, and hide their heads, fearing that ſome plague from heaven was comming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. The Hiſtorian reports of <hi>Caligula,</hi> that wicked Emperour, that he which did ſo much deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the Gods, upon the leaſt crack of thunder, or flaſh of lightning was wont to wink, &amp; to wrap up his head; and if the thunder, and lightening were a little greater then ordinary, he would get off the bed on which he lay, and hide himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bed. Yea, it was a<note n="a" place="margin">Moris fnit cùm tonaret aut fulgeret, aut terra mo veret, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuò pro mutua ſalute diis vota fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere <hi>Cauſab.</hi> ex <hi>Philoſtrato</hi> Cuſus verba apponit</note> Cuſtome among ſome of the Heathens, when there was thunder, or lightening, or an earth-quake to pray to their Dietyes for on anothers ſafety and preſervation. Nay, the very devills in hell <hi>believe, and tremble,</hi> the ſcripture ſaies it, and it is ſo: they have ſeen all the judgments that have been already execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they know them to be his judgments, and tremble at them. They know all the threatnings of the word to be true; and beleeve they ſhall be a-compliſhed. They know that the day of judgment will come, they look for it, and tremble at the thoughts of it. What art thou worſe then the wickedeſt heathen that ever was? then the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Fiend in hell? Oh wretched creature! Pluck off the vizard, ſhew what thou art. Do not defile, &amp; abuſe that pretious name of Chriſtian: thou a Chriſtian, and worſe then a Heathen, worſe then the very devills in hell?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not to acknowledge God in ſuch terrible aſtoniſhing things as theſe are, it is the flatteſt moſt down right Atheiſme that ever was. It is to deny
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50496:31"/>God himſelfe, that there is ſuch a Majeſty as the Majeſty of heaven and earth, it is to deny the word, it is to deny all his judgments, it is in effect to call all the great workes of God that ever he hath wrought in the world meer accidents, and chances: it is to make the floud a meer chance, it is to make the burning of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> a meer chance, in a word it is to make every thing that is recorded in ſcripture as a puniſhment of ſin and ſinners meer caſualities and chances. Oh mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, abominable blaſphemy! was there ever greater blaſphemy then this? This is to deny God, to deny his word, to become a ſtark downright<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hier. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Tragieus quidam apud Lypſ.</note> Atheiſt. Doeſt thou believe there are any ſuch things as judgments: certainly if there be this was one What is a judgment, but onely a puniſhment laid on men for ſin, and that which makes it more remarkeably a judgment is, when men are taken in the midſt of their ſins. Now that ſtage-plaies, are ſins, fearfull and abominable ſins, both in them that act them, and them that behold them, we need not labour much to proove.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We might urge, where doth the word of God tolerate ſuch Paſ-times? the word ſayes we ſhould <hi>redeeme the time, be ſwift to ſpeak, watch unto pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> If thou canſt not afford one houre to heare a Sermon, to pray, to performe religious dueties in,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.16. James 1.19. 1 Pet. 4.7.</note> doth the word afford thee, three, foure houres, or whole nights to ſit up at a play?</p>
            <p n="2">2. But this is leaſt of all; ſtage-playes are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely againſt the word, the word forbids idle words, fooliſh words, jeſting, it forbids unchaſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50496:32"/>lookes, unchaſt apparrell, unchaſt geſtures, every thing that might be an occaſion of ſin: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever looketh upon a woman to luſt after her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>hath committed adultery with her alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in his heart.</hi> Againe it ſayes <hi>The light of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the eye, if thine eye be evill thy whole body is full of</hi> darkneſſe:<note place="margin">Math. 6.22.23.</note> ſtage-playes are ſtuff'd with ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, filthy, unbecomming ſpeeches, paſſages, and geſtures: they are the incentives, &amp; occaſions of all luſt: ſtage-playes are the very acting of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they are a teaching of men to be vile, and wicked. What are all your Comedies, but onely bringing the wanton luſts of men upon the ſtage? as if ſo be the hearts of men were not corrupt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by nature, but they muſt needs ſee lewdneſſe, and folly acted before their eyes, to provoke them to be wicked. Oh horrible! men are not content to be laſcivious, unchaſt in their thoughts, deſires, and inclinations when they are at home, but they would faigne ſee luſt acted in the life of it, they would faigne ſee it diſplayed in its colours. Is not this abominable? <hi>Ezekiel.</hi> 23.14.15.16. <hi>When ſhe ſaw men pourtrayed upon the wall the images of the Chaldeans pourtrayed with vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milion, girded with girdles upon their loynes, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in dyed attire upon their heads, all of them Princes to look to, after the manner of the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of Chaldea the land of their nativity, &amp; as ſoon as ſhe ſaw them with her eyes, ſhe doted upon them, and ſent meſſengers unto them in Caldea.</hi> Could dead pictures do ſo much, a few painted images on a wall? what then will living pictures do? The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50496:32"/>perſons of men acting the part of ſome found and wanton lover, or in another habit repreſenting the amorous looks, carriage, and deportment of ſome lewd and wanton Queane. They, when they ſaw the pictures in the wall <hi>Doted</hi> on them, and doth not the ſight of luſtfull amorous ſpectacles beget &amp; ſtir up luſt? doth it not bewitch and enchant the hearts of men? There are two ſad<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>See D Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of ſtage playes. <hi>p. 51.</hi>
               </note> examples of this in Hiſtories. Beſides, do not men attire themſelves in womans habits, and is not this a ſin? <hi>Deuteron.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The woman ſhall not weare that which pertaineth to a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prinus</hi> Hiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riom maſtix. p. 392. &amp; ſcy.</note> 
               <hi>neither ſhall a man put on a womans garment, for all that do ſo, are an abomination to the Lord thy God.</hi> Is there any thing more cleare, or more expreſſe? How fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent is this in ſtage playes? was it not ſo in the late play? was there not one that acted a womans part in <hi>womans garments?</hi> If we believe the word, theſe were not ordinary ſins, no, they are unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, abominable practiſes, the authors of them are abominable, they are<note n="*" place="margin">Abo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>inabilis eſt apud Deum <hi>hoc eſt Deus abhorret ab his monſtrjs.</hi> Johannes Wolphius. in Deut.</note> 
               <hi>monſters</hi> in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as a learned man explaines that text.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The hand of God hath remarkably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againſt the actors and frequenters of ſtage playes.<note n="*" place="margin">Theatre of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> 
               <hi>There was a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that went to the Theatre to ſee a play, and returned home poſſeſſed with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit: who being rebuked in a conjuration, for daring to aſſault one of the faith, that profeſſed Chriſt; anſwered, that he had done well, becauſe he had found her upon his own ground.</hi> Here you have the devils own confeſſion, he acknowledges ſtage playes to be ſinnes, he had her upon his own ground, where
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50496:33"/>he would have her, and therefore he claimes a right to do what he did. Many inſtances there are in this kind. He that hath a mind to ſatisfy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe may read Mr <hi>Prin's Hiſtrio-Maſtix,</hi> where there are many Pages to this purpoſe. There is one inſtance ſo neere a kin to that of <hi>Witny,</hi> that it may not be omitted. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the</hi> 13 <hi>of January, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1583. <hi>being the Lords day, an infinite number of people, men, women, and children, reſorted unto Paris garden to ſee Beare-baiting, playes &amp; other paſ-times and being all together mounted aloft upon their ſcaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds and galleries, and in the midſt of all their jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and paſtime, all the whole building (not ſo much as one ſtick ſtanding) fell down miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ground with much terror and confuſion in the fall of it; five men and two women were ſlaine out right, and above one hundred and fifty perſons more ſore wounded and bruiſed, whereof many dyed ſhortly after, ſome of them having their braines daſhed out, ſome their heads all to quaſht, ſome their leggs broken ſome their armes, ſome their backs, ſome one hurt ſome another: there being nothing heard there, but woefull ſcreekes &amp; cries, wch did even pieree the skies: children there bewailng the death and hurts of their parents, Parents of their children: wives of their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and Husbands of their Wives; ſo that every way from foure of the Clock in the afternoone till nine at night, eſpecially over London bridge; many were carried in and led betwixt their friends, and ſo brought home to their houſes with ſorrowfull heavy hearts, like lame cripples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Much more might be ſaid to proove the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominableneſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50496:33"/>of theſe playes, <hi>from the riſe and originall of them,</hi> they being the inventions of the Heathens, deviſed and framed on purpoſe to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their<note n="l" place="margin">Graeci om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Gods withall, eſpecially <hi>Bacchus</hi> their Drunken God, from whence ſtage players were called <hi>Bacchus his handy-crafts-men.</hi> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>maine ends</hi> lookt at in them,<note n="m" place="margin">ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sed cum veri Dei notitiam a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſerunt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bacchum feſtivitatis authorem dixerunt, haue ſcenicos ludos conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crarunt: huic dramaticam poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m &amp; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſam <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> dicarunt, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> antiqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: cam ob ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſam <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> appellarunt, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enes ideo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> per dicti. IIs;aa. <hi>Caſaub.</hi> de Satvr. Grae. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. &amp; Rom. Saty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. m E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem Comaediae ſmis non fere alius crat Gracis, quam latitia &amp; hilaritus Cael Rhod. lib 6. at quae ſequuntur, ne referam vetat pudor &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſinfull mirth and jollity.</hi> From the ordinary <hi>concomitants, effects, and fruits of them.</hi> But theſe have been ſo largely handed by Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> and others, that it would be needleſſe to repeat them. There hath been ſaid enough already to prove ſtage playes to be ſinfull. And if ſo, (that we may returne to that where we left) Is it not a judgment if a man be taken in the midſt of his ſinnes? When <hi>Nadab</hi> &amp; <hi>Abihu</hi> were ſmitten by the Lord in the midſt of their ſinnes, was it not a judgment, a ſore judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The ſtory you have, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1.2. Oh ceaſe to ſpeake againſt the God of heaven any more in this ſort. Certainly it was a judgment, and a manifeſt judgment, it was wrath from heaven, yea it was wrath from heaven againſt you in this place. Suffer me to give you this obſervation. All that were killed were the people of Witny; they were your children, your ſonnes and your daughters that were ſlaine; Why ſhould five of Witny be ſlaine outright, and not any one of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. This Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>edy was acted in other places, but it was in <hi>Witny</hi> only that it proved a Tragedy. O <hi>Witny, Witny,</hi> the Lord is angry with thee, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50496:34"/>there are ſeverall ſins among you, that the Lord points out by this judgment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is the ſin of Prophaneneſſe amongſt you, how many are there in this place, that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven only to drinking, ſporting, merriments, and paſ-times? I have too ſadly obſerved it in paſſing the ſtreets, people will ſit drinking in an Ale-houſe making themſelves merry with a Fiddle, whereas they will not ſtep over their threſhold to heare a Sermon. Oh this is the very depth of prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when men care not for God, they care not for his word, they care not for his ordinances, they care not for the great things of ſalvation, but are ſtill calling for their ſports and merriments, they will be jovall and merry, that they will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16. <hi>Lest there be any prophane perſon as Eſau,</hi> that is an unhallowed, and unſanctifyed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, one that ſtill lyes in his naturall filth.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Why what is the Character of ſuch a one? it is added, <hi>who for one morſell of meat ſold his birthright.</hi> You of this place have had the Goſpell amongſt you, Chriſt and ſalvation is offered, heaven and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſtand waiting on men, few men care for this, few men bid Chriſt and ſalvation welcome: are not many apt to ſay, what need of all this preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was it not better with us when we had leſſe? Many think it much to afford one houre in a week to heare a Sermon, but they ſay, come let us eat, and drink, and make our ſelves merry, let us dance it, and card it, and be joviall whilſt we may: and I would to God there may be none ſuch found among you, that will ſit up whole nights at
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50496:34"/>Cards and Dice, that can ſit day after day, many houres together in an Aſehouſe, that grudge a few minnutes to be ſpent in the ſervice of God. Oh! deſperate prophaneneſſe, abominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! the God of heaven hath revenged this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe this day. Do but thinke with your ſelves, what the place was, where the hand of the Lord was ſeen: was it not in ſuch a <hi>Kind of place,</hi> where ſuch meetings uſe to bee: I ſpeake not of that <hi>Particular houſe,</hi> but that it ſhould be in an Inne, Taverne, or Ale-houſe, ſuch a <hi>Kind of place</hi> to which the people of this place are ſo much adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, which they haunt ſo much, &amp; ſpend ſo much time in. Is there nothing to be learn't from this? Doth the Lord point out nothing of the ſin of this place herein? The ſinne of drunkennes is to rife &amp; common amongſt you? the drunkards are reeling in your ſtreets, they are open and obvious, to the view of all, I my ſelfe have been too ſad an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another ſin that may be feared to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt, you is the ſin of uncleanneſſe. Is there no fornication, no adultery in ſecret corners? no ſuch things as chambering and wantoneſſe to be found amongſt you? Examine well what all your ſongs, &amp; carolls are, which are ſo often ſung at your dores, &amp; in your houſes? are there none of them baſe, filthy, obſcene. It argues too too light and wanton a ſpirit, that ſo many ſcores, yea ſome hundreds ſhould be at a laſcivious play. Oh this is a fearful ſin, the ſin of uncleanneſſe, fornication, adultery, and thoſe things that border on it. Theſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50496:35"/>ſins bring aſtoniſhing judgments. Some ſins of this nature were they that deſtroyed Sodom, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fire to come down from heaven upon it. <hi>viz:</hi> the ſin of uncleanneſſe, and unnaturall luſts. Theſe things are too fowle to be named, theſe things are enough to make the ſun in the firmament to bluſh and be aſhamed, and the light of the day to hide and couer it ſelfe, in which there is mention made of ſuch things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third ſin, which is too viſible and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, is, Neglect of the word and ordinances. Some of them that did attend upon the ordinances have turned their back upon them, and the generality amongſt you doe apparently ſleight them. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly what flockinge hath there been to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons? how hath this place been filled every Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, &amp; corner crowded? No people ſo famous for readineſſe, &amp; diligence in hearing the word as the people of Witny: Miniſters that have occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally preached among you have obſerved it, your Name hath been famous amongſt others. How thin are your Congregations grown upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lords day? how ſmall an handfull there are upon Lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure dayes, I am to ſad a witneſſe? Brethren, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to ſpeak my feares. I feare one of the great ſins that bath pluct down this judgment, was the neglect of the Goſpell. It was not long ſince, the laſt time that ever I preacht amongſt you on the Lords day, in a full aſſembly, I beſeeched you, I intreated you by all the arguments of love, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, ſweetneſſe, that poſſibly I could to attend upon the word. I beſeecht you by the love of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50496:35"/>God, by the mercies of the Lord, by the bowells of his goodneſſe, that you would not sleight the word. The Text was from that of St. <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn: 4.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>God is love,</hi> and the poynt from it was, <hi>that the Love of God monifested to the world in the diſpenſation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by Jeſus Chriſt, it was the moſt peereleſſe, match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, incomperable love, that ever was.</hi> Hence were you called upon in ſuch exhortations as theſe in the Applciation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh do not grieve ſuch a Love! doe not ſleight it! doe not abuſe it! Oh unkind ſinner! Oh hard-hearted ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner! worſe then the blackest divell in hell! that canſt be drunk, that canſt ſweare, that canſt laugh at holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the face of that very Love which is come to ſave thee, to pardon thee; that hath ſent the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne that thou might'ſt have life through him. Do not ſin against this love, do not grieve it: ſuffer this love to attaine its ends, to accompliſh its deſires. The deſigne of love is to bring thee unto life, and it hath cost it deare to bring about that deſigne, the ſonne of God muſt come downe from heaven to bring this to paſſe, and is that ſo ſmall a matter? why ſhould any of us be willing to ſtop this love in its wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, to hinder it in its aimes and intentions: all the deſigne of this love is to bring us unto life, and is there any harme in that? Ah, my Brethren, is Death ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, Eternall death, ſuch a ſweet, ſuch a pleaſant thing, that we ſhould be in love with it? Is wrath, the wrath of the Almighty, everlaſting wrath a thing to be deſired? that we ſhould refuſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the offers of eternall love, when it comes to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer life and ſalvation.</hi> With many more Reaſonings
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50496:36"/>in this kind. After this you were exhorted <hi>to make uſe of the meanes of life and of ſalvation,</hi> in ſome ſuch words as theſe. <hi>If you are willing to come to the Lord Jeſus for life, you cannot be unwilling to attend upon thoſe meanes, and that word, that holds forth Chriſt and ſalvation. Will any one ſay that that man prizes a pardon, that will not vouchſafe ſo much as to look upon it, nor to read it, when it is ſent unto him? Oh my Brethren! the Goſpell is the word of life, the word of peace, of pardon, and of ſalvation, can he be ſaid to prize ſalvation and Chriſt, that will not come to that word which brings Chriſt, ſalvation, and all? Is that man willing in good earnest to be ſaved (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever all men ſay they are willing, God forbid els, but is he ſo in good earneſt?) that will not ſtep over his threſhold to heare a Sermon, where this goſpell is brought, &amp; the mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſalvation te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred? I beſeech you ſuffer me to ſpeake to you in the name of the Lord; I beſeech you in the name of Jeſus Christ, I beſeech you in the bowells of Jeſus Chriſt, if you think this loue of God the greateſt love that revealeth pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, life, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſalvation, do not think it much to wait upon the word that reveales it, and makes it manifeſt. Faith commeth by hearing, and hearing is the ordinary meanes to beget Faith, and ſo to bring to Chriſt, and to ſalvation. I beſeech you do not ſleight this Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; if you do, I muſt tell you, (though I am loath ſo to do, yet I am constrained) this Sermon will riſe up in judgment againſt you at the laſt day, and I muſt come in as a witneſſe against you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were ſome of the arguments wher-with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all you were preſſed; yet not-with-ſtanding all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50496:36"/>theſe beſeechings, and entreaties, to my griefe I obſerved it, ſcarce were there any, that did the more frequent the word preached, &amp; hath not the Lord ſhewen his hand ſeverely? whereas there are ſcarce many Scores that wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to hear the word, there are ſome Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreds will go to ſee a wicked &amp; an ungodly play. Certainly the Lord hath bin ave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for this. Do but read that 10. of <hi>Lu.</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the be ginning &amp; ſo on, at the 5. <hi>verſe</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Into what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever houſe you enter, firſt ſay, Peace be to this houſe.</hi> but what followes? in the 10 <hi>verſe</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>But into whatſoever citty ye enter, and they recieve you not, goe your waies out into the streets of the ſame, and ſay even the very duſt of your citty which clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth on us, we do wipe off againſt you. And then there is a ſad cloſe in v.</hi> 12. <hi>But I ſay unto you that it ſhall be more tollerable for Tyre, and Sidon at the day of judgment, then for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Another <hi>provoking ſin,</hi> is the <hi>ſin</hi> of <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, and irreligion.</hi> Do but read what the Lord Jeſus ſpeakes to the Church of <hi>Pergamos. Rev.</hi> 2.14. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee,</hi> why? what is the matter? <hi>Thou haſt there them that hold the Doctrine of Balaam:</hi> and then againe at the 15. <hi>ve. So haſt thou alſo them that hold the doctrine of the Nicolaitans.</hi> The doctrine of <hi>Balaam</hi> is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>He taught Balaack to caſt a stumbling block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the children of Iſrael, to eat things ſacrificed unto Idolls, and to commit fornication.</hi> The Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epiphanius de Nicolao.</note> 
               <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> was much of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and I bluſh to tell you what it was, they did not onely hold a liberty of uncleanneſſe, but a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50496:37"/>of it. Now what was the quarrell which Chriſt had with this church? thou haſt <hi>there</hi> them that hold ſuch and ſuch things: In thee, O <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> are found ſuch monſtrous, and abominable Doctrines, in thee are found ſuch as maintaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; will ſtand for them: with thee it is that they have their ſeat, and reſidence. Are there not to be found in thee, O <hi>Witny,</hi> corrupt, licentious, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Doctrines? haſt thou not alſo them, that hold them, that contend for them with might &amp; maine? Are there none amongſt you that make a mock of ſin, that make ſin nothing, that hold there is no ſuch thing as ſin? Are there none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, that deny the great fundamentall Doctrines, (which are the very hinges, pillars, and foundations of all religion) denying the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, the immortality of the ſoule, election and reprobation, Heaven and hell, that deny the damnation of any, and maintaine the ſalvation of all, that can take away the ſcriptures, the whole Bible, and religion it ſelfe all at once, are there none ſuch as theſe are? Theſe are ſad provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, black and diſmall provocations! I would feigne believe ſome poore ſoules are led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide through weakneſſe, and ſimplicity, and are beguiled through the ſubtility of that old ſerpent whoſe wiles they are ignorant of. The good Lord deliver them, that they periſh not. Its a dangerous thing to ſtumble at the fundamentalls of religion, and godlineſſe, although it be through weakneſſe. But if there be any ſuch who obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and pertinatiouſly maintaine ſuch Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50496:37"/>againſt cleare and convincing light former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhining on them, againſt the truth which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they owned and profeſſed, they are in a ſad and fearfull caſe. Read the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Peter, and Jude,</hi> and there you will ſee the ends of thoſe men 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>They bring upon themſelves ſwift deſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruction. v.</hi> 3. <hi>Their Judgment now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation ſlumbereth not. Ep. Iude, v.</hi> 4. <hi>who were before of old ordained to this condemnation.</hi> If a man out of deſpight make a mock of Preaching, ſabbaths, ordinances, if there be any worſe place in hell it is reſerved for that man.</p>
            <p>You ſee what the ſinnes are which are found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, I have now ſhewen you your wounds, my next work is to endeavour the healing of them, and indeed that was my maine intention, it was not a pleaſure to me to ſearch and lance your your ſoares, yet that was neceſſary to a cure.</p>
            <p>The maine exhortation preſſed on you, hath been an exhortation to repentance, to ſerious, to ſpeedy repentance. And that which remaines, is to give more particular direction, what your carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and deportment ought to be under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hand of God. There are theſe foure things you ought to ſet before you, and to have in your eye.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The work of Humiliation.</item>
               <item>2. The work of Reconciliation.</item>
               <item>3. The work of Reformation.</item>
               <item>4. The work of Remembrance: (for ſo it may be called) laying it as a ſolemne charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50496:38"/>your ſelves to keep in remembrance this ſtrange and wonderfull providence.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Duty to be ſet upon is the work of Humiliation. I do not meane you ſhould ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it in your own ſtrength, but take the ſtrength of Chriſt with you, and the ſtrength of the ſpirit with you, and then you may go on. You have ſinned greatly, oh humble your ſelves greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord! <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> did ſo after his great ſinnes, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12. <hi>And when he was in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, he beſought the Lord his God, and humbled himſelfe greatly before the God of his fathers.</hi> Every particular ſoule ſhould humble himſelfe for his particular ſinnes, and ſay, Good Lord! what have my ſinnes been, that ſuch wrath ſhould come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Witny</hi> in my dayes! Every family ſhould mourne, and lament over the ſinnes of that fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Huſbands ſhould mourne apart, and the Wives a part, children a part, and ſervants a part; every one mourning for his owne perſonall ſinnes, and the family ſinnes. In the 12. <hi>Zachar.</hi> 11. we read of <hi>a great mourning,</hi> a great mourning indeed, <hi>as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon.</hi> When was that? When that good King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was ſlaine. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.23.24.25. Oh that was a dreadfull, a terrible Judgment to have ſuch a Prince taken from them! and this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned a great mourning, the text ſaies, <hi>all Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, and Ieruſalem mourned for Ioſiah.</hi> All were turned mourners then, and there was no one but bare a part in theſe lamentations. <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>he lamented for Ioſiah, and the ſinging
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50496:38"/>men, and the ſinging women ſpake of Ioſiah in their lamentations unto this day.</hi> Their ſinging was turned into mourning, and their rejoycing into lamentation. You have had a great many ſinging men, and ſinging women in this place, ſuch as would goe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doore to doore ſinging their ſongs and carolls to make themſelves and others mirth Oh! it were well if your ſingers were turned into mourners! if your harpers were turned into lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters! if inſteed of al your ſongs &amp; carols, &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cings, you would now come and weep together, and ſay as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> doth. <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.1. <hi>How hath the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger?</hi> How hath the Lord covered poore <hi>Witney</hi> with a cloud in his anger? and as it is in the 4. verſe. <hi>He hath bent his bow like an enemy, he ſtood with his right hand as an adverſary, he powred our his fury like fire.</hi> Complaine as the Church alſo doth in Lam. 3. with a little change in the expreſſion. We are the people that <hi>have ſeen affliction by the rod of his wrath.</hi> v. 3. <hi>Surely againſt us is he turned, he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his hand all the day. v.</hi> 4. <hi>our fleſh, &amp; our skin hath he made old, he hath broken our bones.</hi> Thus I ſay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; weep together, every ſoule ſhould weep, &amp; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry family ſhould weep, &amp; the whole Town ſhould weep, and indeed it were well if God would put it into your hearts to keep a day of weeping, to ſet apart ſome ſolemne day, to faſt and pray, and weep, and humble your ſelves before the Lord. Say unto the Lord as it is <hi>Lam.</hi> 1, 18. <hi>The Lord is righteous, for we have rebelled againſt his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements:</hi> and as the Church bemoanes her ſelfe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50496:39"/>
               <hi>Lam:</hi> 3.39, 40, 41, &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore doth a living man complaine, a man for the puniſhment of his ſins? let us ſearch and try our wayes, and turne again to the Lord. Let us lift up our heart with our hands unto God in the heavens. We have tranſgreſſed, and rebelled, thou haſt not pardoned. Thou haſt covered with anger, and perſecuted us: thou haſt ſlaine, thou haſt not pittied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Aime at Reconciliation. The Lord is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, he hath been highly provoked: oh labour to get his anger removed, and his wrath pacifyed! Run apace to the Lord Jeſus, entreat him to ſtand betweene you, and his fathers wrath: go to, him ſpeedily, go to him immediately, before far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wrath breake forth. It is not all our teares (though we could poure out whole rivers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that can waſh away one ſin: no, no, <hi>in that day</hi> ('tis ſpoken immediately after the mention of that <hi>great mourning</hi>) <hi>there ſhall be a fountaine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>and for uncleanneſle.</hi> Mourne you muſt, mourne greatly, mourne bitterly, yea, but it is the <hi>fountaine</hi> that muſt waſh away ſin, it muſt be the fountaine of the Lord Chriſts blood, that muſt waſh away the fowle, and horrible ſins of <hi>Witney.</hi> Come then, waſh in this fountaine, waſh, and you ſhall be cleane. In the 16 of <hi>Numbers</hi> we read of great wrath: no ſooner had God executed that fearfull judgment upon <hi>Korah,</hi> and his rebellious compa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y, but the people fell to murmering imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. v. 41. <hi>But on the morrow, all the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the children of Iſrael murmered againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and againſt Aaron, ſaying, ye have killed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50496:39"/>of the Lord.</hi> Oh deſperate, and adventrous ſinners! that when they ſaw the judgment of God executed the very day before, yet they fell into the ſame ſins, which they were guilty of, which had been ſo plagued. How angry is the Lord for this, v: 44, 45. <hi>And the Lord ſpake unto Moſes ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, get you up from among this congregation, that I may conſume them as in a moment.</hi> But what doth Moſes do in this caſe? v: 46. <hi>And Moſes ſaid unto Aaron, Take a cenſer, and put fire therein from off the Alter, and put on incenſe, and go quickly unto the congregation, and make an atonement for them, for there is wrath gone out from the Lord, the plague is begun.</hi> This repreſented the mediation of Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.12.</note> who is ſaid to <hi>make interceſſion for the tranſgreſſors.</hi> He is that <hi>Angell</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that <hi>ſtands at the Alter, having a golden cenſer, and much incenſe given to him, that he ſhould offer it with the prayers of thee Saints. chapt.</hi> 8.3. Now <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaies to <hi>Aaron,</hi> go <hi>quickly:</hi> or as it may be read, <hi>make to go with ſpeed,</hi> that is, as the <hi>Chaldee, and Greeke</hi> tranſlateth it, <hi>carry quickly, or in haſte.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Make haſte to the Lord Jeſus, away to him every ſoule of you: all you that have not known what the worth of the Lord Jeſus is till this houre, know now how to prize him, it is he that muſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify the wrath of God that is gone out againſt thee for thy prophaneneſſe, and thine uncleanneſſe, and thy neglect of the word, and thine Atheiſme, Oh fall in love with the incomperably pretious Lord Jeſus this day, as ſoon as ever thou commeſt home fall upon thy knees, &amp; beg thou mayeſt have
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50496:40"/>a Chriſt given to thee: the wrath of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is gone out againſt thee, and will otherwiſe certainly conſume thee. There is no dealing with a ſin-revenging Majeſty, but only in, &amp; by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator. As for you that have intereſt in this preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Name, O make uſe of it, preſent the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſatisfaction of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto the father. It is he that muſt ſtand <hi>betweene the dead, and the living:</hi> ſome are cut off already, and the wrath of the Lord is not yet appeaſed. If you interpoſe not the Lord Jeſus, you may expect more wrath, and more plagues. This I commend to you as the chiefe, and maine direction of all the reſt: it is not all thy careleſneſſe, and ſecurity, it is not all thy ſleighting, and deſpiſing the judgments of God, that will be able to keep off the wrath of the Lord in the end. No, this will bring on thee ſo much the more wrath, and heavyer vengeance: Get into the Lord Jeſus, <hi>hide your ſelves in the clefts of that rock</hi> till this indignation be over paſt. If ever Chriſt be worth having, now is the time. You that cared not for Chriſt when you were at eaſe, and when you lived in pleaſure, my thinkes you ſhould long after Chriſt, and be reſtleſſe till you have gotten him now judgment is come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. Oh, Brethren, if the Judgments of God in this world be ſo terrible, that they are enough to abaſh, and appale the ſtouteſt ſinners, how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and how dreadfull will that laſt, and great day of judgment bee? If thou canſt not ſtand before an angry God now without a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, without an advocate to plead thy cauſe, when
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50496:40"/>he doth but manifeſt a little of his diſpleaſure, and gives but a gentle touch of his finger, how wilt thou ſtand before him without a Saviour, and an advocate? when he ſhall come with millions of Saints and Angells, when the Bookes muſt be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and every mans life ripped open, and it ſhall be ſaid, There waſt thou drunk in ſuch a corner, there hadſt thou thy wanton dalliances upon ſuch a bed, at ſuch a time didſt thou revile at the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, and mock at his waies and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of them, ſo many yeares thou livedſt in the world, and yet never didſt ſtudy how thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt come to the knowledge of God, or the way to life and happineſſe; when all this, and much more ſhall be ſaid; and then the Lord ſhall not come to let in a veine of his wrath only; but he will pluck up all the ſluces, &amp; open all the floud-gates of his wrath, and vengeance, when that diſmall place of torment ſhall be ſet before thee, where thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencheable flames are, where thou ſhalt heare the devills roaring, the damned yelling, and ſee all this prepared for thee, how wilt thou be able to hold up thy head at ſuch a day? Make ſure of Chriſt betimes. They were the laſt, and dying words of one, who in his life time was the Jewell, and Paragon of Religion, and piety in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where he lived. <hi>Make ſure of Chriſt.</hi> He is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then all the gold and treaſures in the world, better then the Rubies, or the Onyx ſtone. Thou art eternally happy if thou get him, and Eternally miſerable if thou come ſhort of him.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50496:41"/>
            <p n="3">3. The next thing that is to be ſtudied, and endeavoured after is Reformation. It is Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the Lord looketh after. Do you think that the Lord delighteth in the death of your children? that he taketh pleaſure in the breaking, bruiſing of your bones? is it matter of joy to him to ſee the hurts, and heare the dolefull complaints of your wives, ſervants, and neere relations? No, no, <hi>God is love,</hi> as you have many times heard had not your ſinnes put him upon it, there had not been ſo ſad a ſpectacle found amongſt you. Put away therefore that evill thing which is in the middeſt of you. When the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had fallen before their enemies, <hi>Achan</hi> who had taken the accurſed thing, and been the occaſion of the miſery, and diſtreſſe that fell upon them, muſt be found out, and ſtoned: You have ſeene already ſome of the <hi>Achans</hi> that have troubled your peace, ſtone them now, and put them to death. You have heard it was the prophaneneſſe, the u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the contempt of the Goſpell, the Atheiſme, and irreligion that is among you, that hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all your trouble: put away theſe accurſed things. And here let me ſpeake more fully to you under theſe foure heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To the looſer, and prophaner ſort.</item>
               <item>2. To them that formerly haue been profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, but now are fallen off.</item>
               <item>3. To them that do ſtill feare the Lord, and hold on in his way.</item>
               <item>4. To all the people of the place in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50496:41"/>
            <p n="1">1 To the looſer, &amp; prophaner ſort, the exhortation is, Oh put away all your drunkenneſſe, formication, uncleanneſſe, oathes, blaſphemies; let him that was filthy be filthy no more; let him that ſtole ſteale no more: oh that you would think of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all theſe baſe, unworthy, deſperately fooliſh wayes, and think of turning to the Lord with your whole heart, and your whole ſoul! You that have layen rotting, and ſtinking in your luſts ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares together, thou that art an old gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed ſinner, think at laſt of returning to the Lord. Ah poor creatures! what meane you? will you ruine the place you live in, and damne your own ſoules eternally? If men had but common humanity in them they would not continue in their groſſe, and hideous abominations, that would pull downe wrath upon their wives and children, friends and neighbours, the towne and place in which they live. But this is a ſmall matter in compariſon; if they had but a tender regard of their own ſoules, if they made any account of their owne ſalvation, if they had but ſo much as a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of ſelfe-love in them, they would caſt away thoſe ſinnes, that will certainly damne them in the end. There is none of the ſinnes which thoulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt <hi>ſo dearly</hi> and huggeſt them with ſo much ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and will not be brought to part with them upon any termes, (thou hadſt rather part with thy life then with ſuch a luſt) there is none of theſe thy moſt beloved ſinnnes, but it will coſt thee the loſſe of everlaſting life, it will coſt thee the loſſe of God, It will coſt thee the loſſe of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50496:42"/>Kingdome of Heaven. The word ſpeakes it out aloud. <hi>No fornicator, nor Idolater, nor adulterer, nor effeminate perſon, nor theefe, nor covetuous perſon, nor drunkard, nor reviler ſhall ever inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 6. Poor man, doeſt thou know what the Kingdome of God meaneth, from whence thou art for ever to be ſhut out? or doeſt thou know what that <hi>for ever</hi> is, which is the line and meaſure of thy torments? Sit downe, and pauſe a while, and think what eternity is: thy life is but a minnute, a dreame, a ſhaddow, it is gone before thou think of it: count over the houres of the day, and is the day ſo long a thing, it is but the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a few ſuch, and then there is a period ſet to all thy pleaſures. How quickly mayeſt thou on thy death-bed look over all thy life paſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it as a very little thing, as a meer point, and beginning only of that which is life? but canſt thou look beyond eternity? canſt thon conceive when everlaſtingneſſe will have an end? all thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are gone and paſſed, they are paſſed over as in a dreame, and now thou art in the midſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity before thou art aware. How fearfull then will theſe thoughts be: what muſt I be <hi>ever</hi> thus? Muſt I be tormented in theſe flames without end? Is there no hope, no poſſibilities of being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then I am? After I have ſuffered ſo many millions of yeares; is there <hi>for ever</hi> ſtill behind? Try a little in thine owne thoughts, and ſee where thou canſt put bonds, and limits to that which is <hi>for ever.</hi> Try where thou canſt put a ſtop, beyond which thou canſt think of no more: is it better to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50496:42"/>be everlaſtingly happy, or everlaſtingly miſerable after a ſcore for two of yeares? Think of theſe things, I beſeech you by all the calls, mercies, judgments of the Lord, by all the riches of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, forbearance, long-ſuffering exerciſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you. Oh do not put off the thoughts of theſe things, Do not any more <hi>chuſe abominable things which his ſoule hateth. Seek ye the Lord, while he may be found, call ye upon him while he is neer. Let the wicked for ſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts: and let him returne unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To thoſe that have forſaken their former profeſſion, the exhortation to them is, O Returne, Returne to the good old way of God, returne to the ordinances, returne to the uſe and exerciſe of holy duetyes, to the uſe of prayer, confeſſion of fin, and the like: if you do not, fearfull will your Judgment be. I hope ſome of them that are gone aſtray do belong to the Lord, but truly you muſt come back by weeping-croſſe.</p>
            <p>I could tell you ſad ſtoryes in this kind. I ſpeak not by heare-ſay: I have knowen them that have ſmarted deeply for ſleighting the ordinances, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting prayer, for low and undervaluing thoughts of Chriſt and his bloud. I could tell you of ſome, that living under ſuch a temptation but for a week, or two, in that ſhort time had loſt all their former communion with God, and being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ſnare accounted their recovery as a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50496:43"/>new converſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The experience of one in this kind was ſo eminent, that I thought I was bound to make it publick, that it might ſerve to ſtop, and reſtraine them which are ſo prone to apoſtacy in the preſent age, and I ſhall ſet it down, as neer as I can, in the ſame words and expreſſions, as I had it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perſons own hand. <hi>Being not well establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, I was ſoon drawn away in my hearte, ſecretly to decline fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that good old way which formerly I walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, I heard one upon justification, and Christs comming in the fleſh,</hi> &amp; upon that place, <hi>Christ in you the hope of glory, in ſuch a manner as I never heard the like before, that I was struck with amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the manner of his planſible ſpeech. And having heard a good report of the man, and had ſome experience before that he was an able ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to miniſter comfort to them that were in distreſſe, I was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly taken with what came from him. And in his poynt of Iustification, he did labour to beat off from repentance, and from confeſſion of ſin, or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of pardon for ſin, and held it out, that theſe were a calling in queſtion the faithfullneſſe of God; for he ſhewed that all that the Saints had to do, was to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and render prayſe; and as he ſayd, he ſpake his owne experience, that he had found more of God in one dayes walking in beleeving, then in many yeares in walking in that ſtrict courſe of praying, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and keeping dayes of humiliation, and blamed thoſe Miniſters that did hold forth ſuch doctrines. Theſe things he backed on with ſuch Arguments, that it did take much upon the affections of them that heard him. For I never heard him pray, but he would
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50496:43"/>ſometimes give thanks and that ſo ſweetly, that it, did even raviſh the ſoules of them that heard him and did much preſſe on to that duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus hearing him at ſeverall times, by degrees I fell from the good old wayes I was trained up in by my parents, and eſpecially that which God had taught me by faithfull Miniſters, and ſoone was I poyſoned with that Doctrine, which my corrupt nature did ſoone cloſe with; to the great diſhonour of the pretious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to the grieving of the good ſpirit of God, and the wounding of mine owne conſcience, which was not ſoon healed. I began to try concluſions with God, and and walked as a looſe libertine, and caſt of the duty of prayer to God in private, and ſo quickly I loſt my communion with God, and he withdraw himſelfe from me, and left me for a time: and no ſooner had God left me, but Satan came in with his deluſions, and formed himſelf into an Angel of light, and carryed me up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fooles Paradiſe, and lulled me aſleep in ſecurity, and carryed me on in that condition for the ſpace of an yeare and halfe before the Lord awakenened me. And no ſooner had I left ſeeking of God in private, but the Lord left me to publique ſhame; for my heart, and ſtrength was let out in an eager perſuit of the world, and love of the creatures, and a fearfull ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath, which began to be a burthen to me, and I had an odious ſleighting eſteeme of the Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God, and queſtioned their judgments in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the word to the people, and I was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly perplexed with vaine thoughts, and by degrees led into ſuch thoughts as I aw aſhamed to name, and by this the Lord awakened me, for I was exceedingly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50496:44"/>startled at it, and began to conſider with my ſelf, that I was out of Gods way, and therefore out of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. Then I began to remember from whence I was fallen, but it was long ere I could do my first workes, but I was reſolved to turne to my firſt husband, for then it was better with me then now. But I found it a hard pluck before I found my God a reconciled fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pardoning my ſin of Apoſtacy, though I ſought it with bitter teares for the ſpace of halfe an yeare. And I thought to have kept it to my ſelfe, and none ſhould have knowen my trouble, but the anguiſh of my ſpirit was ſo exceeding great, that I could not hide it from God or man, for I was afraid the Lord would have made me a publick example to all that knew me, and that I ſhould have been quite distracted, and ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſtreets like one of thoſe that children run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But when I ſaw there was no remedy, I made my caſe knowen, and got all the helpes I could to ſeek God for me. When I made my approach to God I was beaten back by mine adverſary, and by mine owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing conſcience, which was more to me then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes. And often thoſe words were ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in mine eares. Him that draweth back my ſoule abhorreth, and he that putteth his hand to the plough and looketh back, is not fit for the kingdom of heaven, and woe to you Scribes, and Phariſes hypocrites, and that in the</hi> 6. <hi>of the Hebrews, them that have taſted of the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, if they fall away, it is impoſſible to renew them by repentance, with many more places: and when I would have prayed in private, it was told me that God would not heare me, then I replyed that I hoped God
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50496:44"/>would heare him that ſate at his right hand, but it was replyed to me againe the Lord had ſaid to him, (as he had to Jeremiah) pray not for this people, I was ſo lamentably tortured, I could not ſleep, nor eat, nor take any contentment in any relation I had, and had not the Lord witheld me from that which the devill tempted me unto, I had ſurely ended my life.</hi> So low was this poore ſoule brought, and ſo deep was the diſtreſſe in which the Lord left it before it was recovered &amp; indeed I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not declare all, leaſt this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſhould ſeeme too tedious. But it pleaſed the Lordat laſt mercifuly to recover this poor diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoule, though it were long firſt, (that I may uſe ſome of its own expreſſions) <hi>before the Lord did ſeale unto it its pardon, many a bitter day, and night it did undergoe:</hi> &amp; to this very day it makes ſad, &amp; heavy complaints, &amp; undergoes many a ſharp conflict, but the Lord is pleaſed to ſanctify theſe and former diſpenſations in fuch a way as that there are few Chriſtians in which there is ſo much humility, mortifyedneſſe, ſuch ſweet breathings after God, ſuch high prizings of his preſence, and humble attendance on the ordinances, &amp; frequent uſe of holy duetyes to be found.</p>
            <p>So famous an inſtance as this is might ſerve to poyſe, and ballance the looſe and ficle ſpirits of ſuch who begin to hang off from, &amp; to be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent unto the good waies of God. Beware of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy. Apoſtacy is a fearfull ſin, it is the high way to the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>that ſin which ſhall never be pardoned in this world or in the world to come.</hi> Take heed how you medle with edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooles,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50496:45"/>as the proverbe is. <hi>Whoever falls on this stone it will grind him to powder.</hi> Who ever ſhall claſh with the great Fundamentall Doctrines, the Doctrines about ſin, whether there be any ſuch thing yea or no, touching the reſurrection, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, hell, the laſt Judgment, he that ſhall play, and dally with theſe things, and take liberty to ſpeak for them or againſt them, ſuch wantonneſſe as this is will proove his ruine in the end. Did you not once believe theſe things? were they not once Articles of your faith? how is it that you come to caſt them off? Oh it is the moſt dangerous thing in the world for a man to be medling, and tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering with, and at laſt come to a flat downright denying of the great fundamentall truths of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the things which ſometimes he beleeved and profeſſed the beleife off! this man is in a faire way to the unpardonable ſin: I do not ſay this is that ſin, but he that is come to this had need look to himſelf, he is in the way thereunto without abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of mercy to recover him. Much have thoſe to anſwer for, and fearfull is their Judgment like to be, who peremptorily, and obſtinately main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch deſperate opinions, that all men ſhall be ſaved alike, that ſin is nothing, but only that men make it ſomething by their own Melancholly fancies, and timerous apprehentions.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pete ex ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioribis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocl.</note> This is the very Bane, and cut-throat of all religion, this is that which cuts the very ſinewes of Godlineſſe, this is that which undermines the worſhip of God in the world, and plucks it up by the very rootes. Take away the name, and notion of ſin, make it
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50496:45"/>nothing, who then will regard to worſhip, feare, obey the great God? who will care for any of his commands? Do you not think the Lord is <hi>Jealous</hi> for theſe things? Brethren, my heart will hardly ſerve me to ſpeake of theſe things, its even rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to dye, and ſink within me. Good Lord! what wilt thou doe for thy great Name? how poor? how ſleight? how contemptible a thing do men make of thee in the world? men begin to forget that they are thy creatures, and that thou haſt made them! I could even here break forth into teares, and ſay <hi>Oh that my head were waters and mine eyes a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares that I might weep day, and night</hi> for the diſhonour, ſcorne, and contempt that iscaſt vpon the bleſſed God by theſe things.</p>
            <p>It is time for the <hi>Angells</hi> of the Churches, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,<note place="margin">A briefe addition touching <hi>Atheiſme.</hi>
               </note> and Meſſengers of Jeſus Chriſt to carry that peece of the <hi>everlaſting Goſpell, and to preach unto them that dwell on earth, and to every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 14.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying with a loud voice: Feare God, and give glory to him, worſhip him that made heaven, and earth, and the ſea, and the fountaines of water.</hi> It was ſaid in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his time, that the world was become an <hi>Arrian,</hi> and now it may be ſayed that the world beginnes to turne <hi>Atheiſt.</hi> Some there are that darepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it. One upon that paſſage: <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God,</hi> was not afraid to utter ſuch words, <hi>That foole ſpake the truth.</hi> Oh monſter! eternity will be a thing long enough to torment thee, and make thee feele whether there be a God yea, or no. But it is not all thy blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50496:46"/>can rid thee of thy folly. Canſt thou produce the records of the world for ſix, or ſeaven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares agoe? canſt thou confute the book of Geneſis, and bring to light ſomewhat more ancient, and authentique then it? Canſt thou tell who was Adams Father? and what the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men were before him? riſe up as high in thy thoughts as thou canſt, wilt thou not at laſt come to ſome firſt man? was this man made yea, or no? who was it that made him? was it himſelf. then he was before himſelfe, but was he made by ſome other? who was that? or was he from everlaſting? why then doth he not continue to everlaſting? will any thing deſtroy it ſelfe? Durſt thou truſt thine own ſenſe? are there any ſuch things as ſpirits? if not; why are there ſo many wretched creatures ſuffer for their familiar converſe with them? if thou do believe that there are ſuch things as evill ſpirits, who is it that keepes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in order, &amp; ſetts bounds to their mallice? But ſuch mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters who deny the Principles of their being ſhould be rather hiſſed out of the world with abhorrence, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſputed againſt.</p>
            <p>As there are many that dare <hi>profeſſe Atheiſme,</hi> ſo there are many that durſt <hi>live</hi> it. How pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remtory and reſolved are men in wayes of ſin? how light a thing do they make of the word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and threats of God, and of every thing thing that might keep them in awe, and retaine them in their obedience to their acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and obſervance of the great God? Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to think they are above the word, above hell above damnation, and in effect above God. What a poor, and contemptible thing is religion grown
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50496:46"/>in the world? Certainly, if religion be the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an awe of God upon a mans ſpiritt, the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and binding of the ſoule over to him, the conſtant obſervance of him, and ſtrict conformity to his will, there is little of this religion to be found in the world.</p>
            <p>In all theſe reſpects it becommeth the ſervants of the Lord to beſtirre themſelves, to contend zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly for God, for the cauſe of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to ſuffer the name of God, his worſhip, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelfe to dye, and be forgotten in the thoughts, &amp; lives of men</p>
            <p n="3">3. To you that feare the Lord, and walk on in his wayes, the exhortation to you is, be more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be more humble, be more heavenly minded, be more fruitfull in good workes: <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Seek ye the Lord, all ye meek of the earth which have wrought his Judgment, ſeek righteouſneſſe, ſeek meekneſſe.</hi> Ye that are meek already, ſeek more meekneſſe, ye that have wrought righteouſneſſe, be more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and abound in all the fruits of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Lords eye is more eſpecially ſet upon you, he obſerves in a more peculiar manner what your carriage will be, the Lord expecteth you ſhould not onely mourne for your own ſinnes, but for the ſinnes of the place in which you live. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, me thinkes there is not that growth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you which I could wiſh, I could be glad to ſee more life, more ſweet breathings after God amongſt you. Me thinkes you do not love God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt enough, you diſcourſe of him but ſeldome, and ſpeak of him but coldly. <hi>Ignatius</hi> had his heart ſo inflamed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50496:47"/>with the love of Chriſt, that when he ſpake of him, he would ſay, <hi>My love was crucifyed.</hi> Some are ſo full of love to him, as that they are raviſhed when they think of him, they break out, and ſay, oh that excellent! that incomperable one how preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is the Lord Jeſus! how pretious is he! Men, and Angels are too little to love him, and admire him. For the Lords ſake ſtirre up your ſelves, entertaine Chriſt better, and entertaine the Goſpell better. When the Gentiles heard, that the Goſpell was ſent to them, and thatit appertained to them as well as to the Jewes, it is ſaid, <hi>they were glad, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed the word of the Lord. Acts.</hi> 13.48. Oh this was wellcome newes, joyfull tidings to them indeed! their hearts were even raviſhed, and tranſported with ſuch bleſſed tidings as theſe, that Chriſt ſhould become <hi>ſalvation</hi> to them, as well to the Jewes, for that was it which was made knowen to them in <hi>v.</hi> 47. <hi>They glorifyed the word,</hi> they magnifyed, and advanced the word. Oh this was the beſt word that ever they heard! an excellent, and a ſweet word! I beſeech you, my brethren, ſtirre up your ſelves, <hi>and provoke one another to love, and to good workes.</hi> It is a great fault in the profeſſors of this place, that they maintaine ſuch a diſtance, and ſtrangeneſſe one towards another. The ancient Saints <hi>ſpake often one to another. Malachy:</hi> 3.16. The Primitive Saints in the Apoſtles times met of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, they prayed together, and conferred together. So it ſhould be with you, you ſhould be often viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one another, and aſking each other, Oh my Friend! what are your temptations? what are
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50496:47"/>your comforts? what have the dealings of God been with your ſpirit ſince we mett laſt? is grace kept alive? or is it more dead? This is the way to be a thriving people. I would faine that you of this place ſhould be patternes to all that are round about you for humility, for heavenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſſe, for ſoundneſſe in the faith, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, for holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To all in generall, the Exhortation is, Labour to ſet up religion in this place, ſet it up in your hearts, ſet it up in your families, ſet it up, as much as may be, in the whole towne. Away now with all your ſinfull ſports, and merriments, away with all your cards, and dice, ſinging, dancing, and ſuch like vanityes. Inſteed of theſe things ſet up Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing, praying in the family morning, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and let one neighbour come to another, and ſay, come let us go to heaven together, and ſeek the Lord together. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 50, 4.5. <hi>In thoſe dayes, and in that time ſaith the Lord, the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ſhall come, they, and the children of Judah toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, going &amp; weeping: they ſhall ge, &amp; ſeek the Lord their God. They ſhall ask the way to Zion with their faces thitherward ſaying, come, and let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall covenant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> Oh what a bleſſed change would this bee, if young, and old, rich, and poor, huſb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ands, and wives, parents, and children, maſters, and ſervants would all joyne together; if they would come <hi>weeping</hi> together, and <hi>ſeek</hi> the Lord, if all the people in this place would ſet their faces towards <hi>Heaven,</hi> and toward <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſay,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50496:48"/>Come let us joyne our ſelves in a perpetuall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, we will ſtrike in with the Lord this day, and we will never alter our choice more, it ſhall be a <hi>Covenant that ſhall never be forgotten.</hi> If you would all reſolve this day, Come, we will goe to <hi>Zion with our faces thitherward.</hi> We will go where the word is preached, and where the ordinances are ſet up, and where the worſhip of God is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, oh we will neglect the word no more, &amp; we will neglect the ordinances no longer. This is one of the laſt requeſts I have to leave with you, oh do not neglect the opertunityes of hearing the word, and comming to the Ordinances as you have done For the Lords ſake, you that are maſters of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies come your ſelves, and bring your children, and ſervants along with you; you that have friends, bring your friends with you. Go weeping (as they did) and ſay, oh we have neglected the word, and neglected Chriſt, and neglected ſalvation, but we will neglect them no more. Let that prophecy be fulfilled of you which was ſpoken, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And many people ſhall goe, and ſay, Come ye, and let us goe up to the mountaine of the Load, to the houſe of the God of Jacob, and he will teach us of his wayes, and we will walk in his paths, for out of Zion ſhall goe forth the Law, and the word of the Lord out of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> Redeeme an houre in the week day to heare the word, your callings will not proſper ever the worſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4, The laſt thing I have to propound to you by way of direction, is the Duty of Remembrance. Forget not the Wonderous workes which the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50496:48"/>Lord hath wrought. When mercyes, or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are new, and freſh, we are apt to ſpeak of them, and to be affected with them, but a little time weares them out of our minds, and blots them quite out of our Remembrance. Oh take heed of this. <hi>Bind</hi> this ſad Providence <hi>for a ſigne upon your</hi> hands, and let it <hi>be as Frontlets between your eyes.</hi> Set it down in your <hi>Almanacks,</hi> and keep a Regiſter of the Day: oh this was the black, and diſmall day of Gods viſitation on poor <hi>Witny.</hi> It were good if you kept ſome ſolemne day every yeare as a remembrance of this ſad, and heavy ſtroke. For as great mercyes require great, and and ſolemne praiſes, ſo do great judgments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire great, aed ſolemne humiliation. <hi>They ſpeake of Joſiah in their lamentations to this day, and made them an Ordinance in Iſrael: and behold they are written in the Lamentations.</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25. It ſeemes they had a conſtant remembrance of that judgment (the loſſe of good <hi>Joſiah</hi>) they ſpeak of him <hi>to this day.</hi> It was a conſtant practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them to remember that ſad ſtroke: and they had a ſolemne Book of Lamentations ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to mourne for this judgment. <hi>Luke.</hi> 17.32. <hi>Remember Lots wife.</hi> We have not many ſuch <hi>Remembers</hi> in all the Book of God upon ſo ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all an occaſion, (they may eaſily be all reckoned up) and therefore here is ſome ſpeciall thing hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us. Here was a ſpeciall monument of Gods judgment on a woman that was hankering after her old pleaſures, ſhe had been uſed to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and contentments of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and ſhe was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50496:49"/>loath to part with theſe: ſhe lookt back to the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of her former pleaſures, and contentments, and whilſt ſhe is looking back ſhe became a <hi>Pillar of ſalt.</hi> Oh remember this, (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>Remember Lots Wife.</hi> There is an accent put on this. You of this place have been hankering af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſports, and merriments, you have been migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſet on theſe things, and the Lord hath ſhewen his diſpleaſure by an Eminent hand, and a ſtrech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out arme. Oh remember this, remember the Tragicall ſtory at the <hi>White Hart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have heard now at large what your duty is; in generall it is to fall upon the work of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. You have likewiſe been directed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly how to carry your ſelves in that work; and what the particular Duetyes are which are to be done by you, and what the Lord expects from each of you in your ſeverall rankes, and places. That which remaines is only, in the cloſe of all, to adde a motive, or two (to that which hath been already ſaid) to preſſe that which is your duety on you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you do not repent, ſome worſe thing will come upon you. It may be the Lord may ſend a Fire next to conſume all your houſes, it may be he may ſend the peſtilence among you to devoure you, or if not that, a famine: the Lord hath wayes enough to puniſh unrepentant ſinners. Read over that 26. of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> &amp; there you will ſee what the Lord threatens in ſuch a caſe, <hi>v.</hi> 23.24. <hi>If ye will not be reformed by theſe things, but will walk contrary unto me: then will I alſo walk contrary unto you, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50496:49"/>will puniſh you yet ſeaven times for your ſinnes. v.</hi> 27 <hi>And if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, but walk contrary unto me: then I will walk contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you alſo in fury; and I, even I, will chaſtiſe you ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times for your ſinnes.</hi> If you think to wax ſtout and ſtubborne againſt the Lord, he will be as ſtout againſt you, if you walk contrary to him he will doe ſo to you, and if one judgment will not do it, he will follow you with a ſecond, &amp; a third, and if you ſtill harden your hearts againſt him, he will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e againſt you in <hi>Fury,</hi> he will ſummon up all his wrath, and vengeance, and if he be able to break, and ruine you, to be ſure he will do it. Oh it is a dreadfull word. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>I will ſet my face againſt you,</hi> and that in the 28. <hi>verſe. I, even I will chaſtiſe you.</hi> As much as if he ſhould ſay, I the great God, I that made heaven, and earth, and can turne the foundation of it upſidedown whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I pleaſe, I will ſet my ſelfe againſt you, I will engage all my wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, and all my power, I will put forth all my glory, and excellency to deſtroy you.</p>
            <p>If temporall judgments will not prevaile, God hath eternall puniſhents in a readineſſe for obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and incorrigible ſinners. <hi>Tophet is prepared, &amp;c.</hi> Hell is in readineſſe, eternall flames, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burnings are prepared; and thoſe that would not be tamed, and brought into order by the judgments of God in this world, will be ſtill and calme enough when they are thrown there. Then thy pride and ſtoutneſſe of heart againſt the Lord, thy ſtubbornneſſe, and incorrigibleneſſe will do thee little good. This hath God prepared,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50496:50"/>
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 7.11, 12, 13. <hi>God is angry with the wicked eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day: if he turne not, he will whet his ſword, he hath bent his bow, and made it ready; he hath alſo prepared for him the inſtruments of death.</hi> Are not the judgments of God in this world terrible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough? do they not ſtrike deep enough? do men beare up themſelves againſt the Almighty, and wax proud againſt him notwithſtanding theſe? Oh! he hath yet a deadly inſtrument left behind, he can ſtrike them into hell, and then they are ſtruck to purpoſe. Art thou not afraid of the firſt death, (the worſt as thou ſuppoſeſt of temporall evills) becauſe that is but a ſhort paſſage? But there is the ſecond death, when thou ſhalt be ever dying, and yet never dye: thou ſhalt be alwayes in the pangs, and agonyes of death, and yet never paſt death it ſelfe. <hi>The judgments of God in this world they are but as the Alphabet, as the A.B.C. to that great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">O quantum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit iſtud Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorium, quod Majeſtate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina apparen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, &amp; to mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus Angelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum celebrabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; quanto majoris Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatis, tanto majoris terro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp; horror is erit impi is. <hi>Luth.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and laſt judgment.</hi> It was <hi>Luthers</hi> expreſſion. <hi>Oh how great</hi> (ſayes he againe) <hi>ſhall that conſiſtory be, When the Divine majeſty ſhall appeare, and ſo many thouſand Angels and by how much the greater the Majeſty of that court ſhall be, ſo much greater will the dread, and horror be that will fall upon wicked men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If you be a reformed people, the Lord will delight in this place, as much as ever he hath loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed it. <hi>The Lord doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men.</hi> No, Judgment is his ſtrange work; had you not put him to it, he had never done that which he hath,</p>
            <p>Returne now unto the Lord make a covenant
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50496:50"/>with him this day to ſerve him with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart, and a willing mind. Chooſe the Lord for your God, and give up your ſelves in Chriſt Jeſus to him, to walk with him unto all well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, then will he rejoyce over you to do you good he will ſet himſelfe to bleſſe you with his whole heart, and with his whole ſoule, <hi>Bleſſed</hi> ſhall you be in the <hi>towne, bleſſed in the field, bleſſed in your basket, and bleſſed in your ſtore. Bleſſed when you riſe up, and bleſſed when you lye down.</hi> All the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that paſſe by you ſhall ſay. Behold <hi>Witny,</hi> the Place which the Lord hath bleſſed. The Lord ſhal take away your reproach, and it ſhall no more be ſaid, this is <hi>Witny,</hi> whom the the Lord hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, but this is <hi>Witny</hi> whom the Lord hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whom the Lord delighteth in. Yea, the Lord himſelfe ſhall <hi>Bleſſe you out of Lion.</hi> You ſhall have all the Goſpell mercyes, knowledge ſhall increaſe, and the feare of the Lord abound amongſt you: others ſhall bee provoked by your zeale, they ſhall come, and ſee the religion that is in <hi>Witny,</hi> and ſay: Behold the place that was eminent for <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>judgment,</hi> is now become eminent for <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and mercy.</hi> And now I may ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, after he had thundered out all the curſes, and ſweetly laid forth all the bleſſings of the Lord up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their obedience or diſobedience to the Law, <hi>I have ſet life, and death before you this day.</hi> Oh chuſe the way of life, and you are bleſſed, bleſſed ſhall you here, and bleſſed for evermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:50496:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:50496:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:50496:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:50496:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:50496:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:50496:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:50496:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:50496:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:50496:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:50496:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:50496:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:50496:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:50496:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:50496:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
